<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An explanation of the solemn advice, recommended by the Council in Connecticut Colony, to the inhabitants of that jurisdiction, respecting the reformation of those evils, which have been the procuring cause of the late judgments upon New-England. By Mr. James Fitch ...</title>
            <author>Fitch, James, 1622-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09144</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W24614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922717</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80922717</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2893:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An explanation of the solemn advice, recommended by the Council in Connecticut Colony, to the inhabitants of that jurisdiction, respecting the reformation of those evils, which have been the procuring cause of the late judgments upon New-England. By Mr. James Fitch ...</title>
                  <author>Fitch, James, 1622-1702.</author>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
                  <author>Fitch, James, 1622-1702. Brief discourse proving that the first day of the week is the Christian Sabbath.</author>
                  <author>Connecticut. Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 133 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Green for I. Usher of Boston.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston in New-England. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Increase Mather.</note>
                  <note>"A brief discourse proving that the first day of the week is the Christian Sabbath ... By Mr. James Fitch ..."--P. [73]-[134], with separate t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Boston Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Offenses against religion --  New England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:3"/>
            <p>AN EXPLANATION OF THE SOLEMN ADVICE, Recommended by the <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCIL</hi> in <hi>Connecticut Colony,</hi> to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants in that <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Reformation of thoſe <hi>EVILS,</hi> which have been the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing Cauſe of the late <hi>Judgments</hi> upon <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>James Fitch,</hi> Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Sam. 7.3.</hi>
               </bibl> And Samuel ſpake unto all the houſe of Iſrael, ſaying, If ye do return unto the Lord with all your hearts, then put away the ſtrange gods and Aſhtaroth from among you, and prepare your hearts unto the LORD, and ſerve him only, and he will deliver you out of the hand of the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Chron. 19.4.</hi>
               </bibl> And <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <p>BOSTON IN NEW-ENGLAND. Printed by <hi>S. Green</hi> for <hi>I. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> of <hi>Boſton.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191877:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader,</head>
            <p>COncerning thoſe Brief and Nervous Diſcourſes which are emitted here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, the Reverend and Worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, had no thoughts of Publiſhing them, until ſuch time as others did Importune him thereunto. As for the firſt Treatiſe, it was thus occaſioned.</p>
            <p>In the diſtreſſing time of the late War with the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>N-England,</hi> many of the Rulers (both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical) in <hi>Connecticut Colony,</hi> being ſenſible that publick Judgements ſeldome come, but as Intimations of Heavens diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and that then, of all Men the Leaders of the People are concerned to enquire into the Cauſes of the Lords Controverſie, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1. they did accordingly meet for that purpoſe. The Miniſters drew up in writing what they concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be the mind of God, reſpecting the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Queſtion before them; which <hi>Reſult,</hi> was approved of by their Magiſtrates, and Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the Conſideration of the Inhabitants in that Juriſdiction. This faithful Servant of Chriſt, did wifely take hold on that opportunity,
<pb facs="tcp:191877:5"/>in his publick Miniſtry to inſiſt upon both the <hi>Malady</hi> and the <hi>Remedy,</hi> which there is ſo great cauſe to be enquiring into, and did reduce his Inſtructions into a <hi>Catechetical Method,</hi> for the better edification of the younger ſort in his Congregation. Sundry Perſons of Worth and Judgement hapning to be preſent at ſome of thoſe Exerciſes, were very earneſt to have them made more publick; to gratifie whoſe deſires, the Worthy <hi>Author</hi> has been prevailed with to grant the Copy of what was more inlargedly <hi>viva voce,</hi> delivered. A Diſcourſe of this nature is very ſeaſonable and needful; and I hope will be bleſſed for the good of many.</p>
            <p>As for the ſmall tractate, reſpecting the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabbath;</hi> the Author has (ſo far as I am able to diſcern) with very good judgement and in few words, aſſerted and proved the Truth whoſe confirmation he has undertaken. The moſt plauſible Argument, which our <hi>Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batarians</hi> inſiſt upon is, their pretending the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the fourth Commandment. Nor do we deny but that by virtue thereof, a <hi>ſeventh part of time,</hi> or one day in the <hi>Hebdomadel Revolution,</hi> ought to be kept as an holy Reſt unto God. But it is evident, that ſome expreſſions in the <hi>Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> do in a peculiar manner reſpect the <hi>Jewiſh State.</hi> This is true of the Preface to the Moral
<pb facs="tcp:191877:5"/>Law; and of the promiſe annexed to the fifth Commandment; and ſome particulars in the tenth Commandment, are accommodated to the then ſtate of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And why ſome Expreſſions in the fourth Commandment may not be ſo too, our ſeventh day Men have as yet given us no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and ſufficient reaſon. Nay, the Learned <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves acknowledge it to be ſo. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not offended when they ſee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians doing ſervile works upon the ſeventh day of the week, for they ſay the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to the ſtrict and legal obſervation of their Sabbath. The Jews in <hi>Amſterdam</hi> told <hi>Jackſon, Sands,</hi> and other keepers of the ſeventh day, that except they were alſo Circumciſed, their obſervation of that day was groundleſs. There is no place in the New Teſtament which the <hi>Iews</hi> do ſo much object againſt Chriſtians as <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17, 18. They perverſely cavil and ſay, that the Apoſtles did act contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of their Maſter Chriſt, by telling Men that they ought not to obſerve the Ceremonial Law, <hi>R. Maimon</hi> (<hi>In miſna</hi> L. 1. C. 9.) has a whole Chapter full of Blaſphemy againſt thoſe who teach that the Law is deſtroyed in whole or in part. The moſt Judicious and Learned of our Writers, acknowledge that the place mentioned has reſpect both to the Ceremonial and to the
<pb facs="tcp:191877:6"/>Moral Law; And that as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſet in opppoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as deſtroying is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to fulfilling, chriſt did not evert the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Law. he did himſelf conform to the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the law, and require other men to do ſo, as long as the author of that law did ſee meet to continue it; and every way fulfilled thoſe <hi>Types</hi> which pointed at the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> that was to come. Our <hi>Iewiſh Sabbatarians</hi> who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe thoſe words of Chriſt to countenance their Error; might as well from thence argue that the Ceremonial Law is ſtill in force. For its certain it was not aboliſhed until every tittle contained therein was fulfilled. It has been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that Chriſtians in the Primitive times ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the ſeventh day. The Chriſtian <hi>Iews</hi> in the Apoſtles time had a religious reſpect, not only for the ſeventh day Sabbath, but for Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion and other Ceremonies, until ſuch time as the <hi>Iudaical World</hi> was utterly deſtroyed, but the Apoſtles never allowed Chriſtianized Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſo to <hi>Iudaize.</hi> The <hi>Ebionites</hi> kept the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, but they were never accounted true Chriſtians. The <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> which paſs under the Name of <hi>Clement,</hi> L 7. C. 24. commend the obſervation both of the ſeventh and of the firſt day of the week. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſpeaks of ſome that obſerved both dayes. Such Chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:191877:6"/>were certainly leavened with <hi>Iudaiſm.</hi> At this day, the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Chriſtians obſerve the ſeventh day, they alſo obſerve Circumciſion; and if Men will <hi>Iudaize</hi> in one particular, it is not to to be wondred at, if they be left to <hi>Iudaize</hi> in more. Of later times there have not been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of any great Fame or Note in the World, that have ſtood up for this Opinion. There was in <hi>England</hi> formerly <hi>Braborn</hi> and <hi>Trask;</hi> but they afterwards recanted. Within theſe few years, Mr. <hi>Bramfield</hi> of <hi>Sherborn</hi> was ſtrangely drawn away into this Error. But his weightieſt Objections are anſwered, with great judgment and candour, by the Reverend Mr. <hi>William Ben</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> in <hi>Dorſet</hi> (a Man whoſe Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was occaſioned by a Sermon of his own; after which he continued an eminent Light in the Church of God for fifty years together; and than whom I never knew Man upon Earth that did maintain a greater intimacy of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God) Nor has Mr. <hi>Bramfield</hi> made any Reply to Mr. <hi>Ben</hi>'s Book, ſo far as I have ſeen or heard.</p>
            <p>As for the preſent <hi>Jewiſh Sabbatarians</hi> in <hi>Connecticut Colony</hi> they out-do all their Predeceſſors, as to Inſolent Behaviour, being arrived unto that height of impudent Prophaneneſs, that they fear not in the ſight of the Sun, to bid defiance unto the Chriſtian Sabbath, by following the ſervile works of their particular Callings on the Lords Day. So that it was high time for the Magiſtrate
<pb facs="tcp:191877:7"/>who is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabulae,</hi> to interpoſe. And truly if it had not been ſo, there is reaſon to fear that the hand of Heaven would have done the Magiſtrates work, after a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar more terrible manner. We cannot with truth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that viſible Judgments from Heaven have befallen Chriſtians, for not religiouſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obſerving the ſeventh Day, but Hiſtories abound with Examples of Gods awful and tremendous puniſhments, inflicted upon the Prophaners of the Lords Day; which is a very convincing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the obſervation of the <hi>firſt day of the week</hi> is of Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Objector here Animadverted upon; the truth is, his Allegations are feeble and frivolous, ſo that ſome may think 'tis pity a Man of Mr. <hi>Fitch</hi>'s Strength and Ability, ſhould be improved in a Service which a far meaner hand might with eaſe have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Yet conſidering, that ſometimes as ſenſeleſs an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> as <hi>Mahomet</hi> was, may poſſibly leven a World of deluded Souls, if due care be not taken to prevent it; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have judged it neceſſary that he ſhould be anſwered <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> What is written will tend either to his Converſion (which if poſſible the Lord grant) or elſe to his being left the more inexcuſable &amp; condemned in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, while he oppoſeth the light of Truth. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> does both allow and require, that ſome and in ſpecial <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daizers</hi> ſhould be <hi>rebuked ſharply,</hi> that they may be ſound in the faith, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.13. Had the <hi>Antichriſtian Sabbatarian</hi> here refuted, only modeſtly ſcrupled whether the ſeventh day were not ſtill of Divine inſtitution, more gentleneſs in Expreſſion would have been uſed with him; but he is not a perſon to be <hi>Saved</hi> in that way. If by any means he be plucked out of the fire, neither himſelf, nor thoſe that have aimed at his Salvation, will be ſorry, <hi>Jude</hi> 23. The Lord give a bleſſing to Faithful Endeavours, and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate his Truth, Name, and Sabbath, in ſuch a way as ſhall be moſt for his own Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Boſton <date>
                     <hi>July.</hi> 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>INCREASE MATHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191877:7"/>
                  <head>In Order to ſome <hi>Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Solemn Advice, which our Honoured Magiſtrates did in the Time of our Calamity, ſend abroad unto the ſeveral Churches and Congregations in this Colony, we have occaſion to reflect upon both</head>
                  <p>THe Provocations of <hi>New-England,</hi> and the Impediments of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and to make way for the following Diſcourſe: we may conſider what <hi>Moſes</hi> that great Prophet of the Lord, and chief Ruler in <hi>Iſrael</hi> did incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate upon that People in <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and forget not how thou provokedſt the Lord thy God to wrath in the Wilderneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We ought to have and hold a remembrance what our Tranſgreſſions have been, by which the Lord hath been provoked to wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Remembrance ought to be clear and full: the Pen-men of the Holy Scriptures
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191877:8"/>were moved by the Spirit of God, to Record clearly and fully the Provocations of which the People of God had been guilty, as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. <hi>&amp; Pſal.</hi> 106. and through the Hiſtory of the Church in the Book of God, and ſome of the ſpots of the moſt beautiful Saints, God would not ſuffer theſe to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and left out of the Holy Scripture Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, 1 <hi>King</hi> 15.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.32, 32.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Remembrance ought to be affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, with a heart ſuitably affected; Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring what our cares and fears, grief and tears were in that day, when the wrath of the Lord appeared to be a conſuming fire, and we as combuſtible matter; and had not the Lord quenched the fire of his wrath, with his own Bowels of Mercies, we had periſhed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16 61. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.19, 20.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Remembrance ought to be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly Reforming, conſidering how our ſins have driven us into a perillous ſtate, and we ready to periſh in the Ocean of miſeries, and ſhall we again provoke the Lord to wrath? will he not be angry until he hath conſumed us? <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.14. if we do not remember our Provocations to our Humiliation and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, the Lord will remember them againſt us, to our own confuſion and deſtruction; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:191877:8"/>we waſh our ſelves as with Nitre, and take much Sope, yet our iniquities are marked before the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21, 22.</p>
                  <p>And we may ſee what Record of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences reſpecting a People or particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is moſt agreeable to holy Scripture Rule. That Record which doth declare the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts of the Lord &amp; our unrighteous deeds, the ſuperabounding Grace of God although our ſins have abounded: That Record which doth ſet forth the Lords Juſtice, Mercy, Truth, Faithfulneſs and Almighty arm, by uncovering the feebleneſs, ſickleneſs, falſeneſs, &amp; many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bitter Provocations, both of Rulers &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.7, 8. This is moſt like the Record in Holy Scripture, and the Church Hiſtory therein contained: but ſuch a faithful Record ſeldom comes forth in that age in which the then preſent Providences were acted, few will ſuffer a plain Remembrance of their Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, but the Lord hath hitherto provided ſome faithful Recorder, who hath left that in Record to ſucceeding Ages, which the preſent Generation would not endure to hear of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.36, 37, 38.</p>
                  <p>And that we may have and hold a convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, hearty &amp; Reforming effectual Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance what our Provocations have been; let
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191877:9"/>us conſider according to that moſt Solemn Advice of our Rulers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> What that ſin is which is the root actually and nextly of all the other ſins?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Apoſtaſie from the true Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not only abſolutely but comparatively as it is a declenſion from the ſtricter part of Religion, or a decay of the Beauty of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Profeſſion, and this Apoſtacy doth ſhew it ſelf in the various degrees of it, and in the bitter fruits and effects of the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Apoſtaſie may be taken either Abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or Comparatively. 1. Abſolutely, and ſo its a total turning from the Faith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19, 20. and thus the Apoſtate is become a Blaſpheming Infidel; or a falling from Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Prophaneneſs; &amp; thus the Apoſtate is turn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed like the Dog to his Vomit, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22, or a forſaking all Godlineſs, and godly wayes, and loving the preſent World; and thus the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate is become a meer Worldling, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or Apoſtaſie taken Comparatively.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In compariſon of that which theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors have been and done, and thus they are not the lovers of God, and doers of good works, which ſometimes formerly they have been, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4 5.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:191877:9"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Fallen away in compariſon of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of their godly Predeceſſors, whoſe Children they are after the Fleſh, but not after the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.37.44. a noble Vine, and right Seed in reſpect of their Parentage, but a degenerate Plant in reſpect of their own practice, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.21. and have gone away from the Ordinances of the Lord, from the dayes of their Fathers, and not kept them in that purity and power, as they were left with them by their Predeceſſors, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In compariſon of what they yet profeſs in words to be, but compare their words, and their works, and it is manifeſt that their works do deny what in words they profeſs, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16 concerning that abſolute Apoſtaſie, it is not ſeen in many in <hi>New-England,</hi> nor uſually ſeen in any, unleſs it be in ſome who at firſt are left to Doctrinal Prophaneneſs, by falling into damnable Hereſies, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. and are after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards given up to practical Prophaneneſs, Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Atheiſm: But as to this compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and gradual Apoſtaſie, how far <hi>New-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> is declined from being <hi>New-England,</hi> I muſt leave to the wiſe hearted to judge, and thoſe only are beſt able to judge of this, who are kept in an awakened broken-hearted, and humbly-believing frame, by frequent heart-ſearching
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191877:10"/>and ſelf-emptying tryals.</p>
                  <p>And this comparative Apoſtaſie doth appear.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In Declenſion from the ſtricter part of Religion: an apoſtatizing Profeſſor in his conſultations and contrivements, will chuſe the licencing part of that inſtruction given by Chriſt, to be wiſe as Serpents, but he refuſeth that reſtrictive part to be harmleſs as Doves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16. but happy is he who is harmleſly wiſe, and yet wiſely harmleſs. An Apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Church is intenſely ſet to the extenſion of Church Liberties to the utmoſt extremity of them, that is the licencing part, but will be remiſs in the exerciſe of Church Diſcipline, and to keep the difference clear between the clean and the unclean, that is the ſtricter part of Religion, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. An Apoſtatizing Profeſſor will catch at Chriſtian Liberty to pleaſe the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. but will not ſit as with a knife at his Throat, as the wiſdome of the Spirit of God doth warn in that matter him who is given to appetite, or any ſenſual affection; this is the ſtricter part of Religion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.2. A withering Profeſſor in the midſt of all his Apoſtatizing and degenerate Practiſes wanteth not wit, nor will, zeal nor courage, to do ſome duties in which he can
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191877:10"/>pacifie Conſcience and pleaſe corruption, can honour God and exalt himſelf, and be as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> like the Heifer that loveth to tread out the Corn, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.11. But as to thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in which there muſt be a crucifying of the fleſh and the affections, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. and an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilating the idol ſelf, and that the caſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſelf, ſhall be the way to ſave himſelf, and the hating of life ſhall be the only way to keep it to life eternal. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.25. whatever a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Conſcience may tell an Apoſtatizing Profeſſor of the truth of theſe things, yet an unbelieving and backfliding heart will draw back, for he loveth pleaſures more than to pleaſe God, and the praiſe of Men more than the praiſe of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.42, 43. and thus the declenſion is from the ſtricter part of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or a decay of the beauty of a religious Profeſſion, and this is uſually ſeen:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Either in a palpable neglect of ſome known duty, in which it may be ſaid of him, <hi>thou lackeſt one thing,</hi> Mark 10.21. and is as the deficiency or want of ſome part and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the body which marreth the integrity and compleatneſs of the Man.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or ſome notorious diſordering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing of duties, that one ſervice comes in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191877:11"/>the time and place of another, and not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is comely, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. and this is as a member of the Body out of its proper place, and a want of that beautiful and joyful thing called Order, <hi>Col.</hi> 2, 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or a greatning and heightening the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto ſome leſſer duties, but a neglecting and not having a proportionable regard to the greater duties, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. and this is as the exceſſive greatneſs of a Member above its natural proportion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Or a want of that true, godly, amiable countenance, with which a Service ſhould ſhine, that mixture of a true Goſpel, white and ruddy Complexion, which is made up of a temperate mixture of divers Graces at once manifeſt, and may be compared to the Mirrh with the Spice, the Wine with the Milk, <hi>Can.</hi> 5.1. But a declining Profeſſor is either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreetly zealous, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. or luke warm, neither hot nor cold, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.16. he is either Schiſmatically cenſorious, and ſaith, <hi>Stand by, I am holier than you, Iſai.</hi> 65.5. or is ſo promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly temporizing, that he is mixed among the People, and as a Cake not turned, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.8.</p>
                  <p>The Concluſion of this is, that the Lord in judgement doth withhold from Apoſtatizing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191877:11"/>Profeſſors, thoſe beautiful viſions, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Diſcoveries of his Glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. he doth withdraw the riſing Beams of the Sun of Righteouſneſs, and the ſhadows of the Evening are ſtretched upon them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.4 5. and the temptations of Satan, and the World doth look upon them, and make them Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnt, and Black, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.6. and the Beauty of their viſible Profeſſion, doth languiſh as with pining ſickneſs, their love decayeth and waxeth cold, and iniquity aboundeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12. and if there yet remain ſome good things with an Apoſtatizing People, <hi>yet how is the Gold become dim,</hi> Lam. 4.1. their Profeſſion hath loſt much of that golden ſplendor and precious and pleaſant luſtre. And thus Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy conſidered as a decay of the beauty of a religious Profeſſion, and this maketh way for the clearing of the Reaſon, why Apoſtaſie is the root of other ſins; and that is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe other ſins in nature follow this, and they are as branches or bitter fruits: the ſin of omiſſion, is in nature before the ſin of commiſſion; a neglect of what ought to be done, before the practice of that which ought not to be done; a forſaking the Fountain of living Waters, and then follows, <hi>our hewing Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns which can hold no Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Jer. 2.13.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:191877:12"/>
                  <p n="2">2. The other ſins are (through the Lords juſt judgement) a puniſhment of the former. Apoſtaſie, is puniſhed with many vices, that where Apoſtaſie comes in, behold a troop of other ſins follow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11, 12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24, 25. But of this in that which followeth.</p>
                  <p>Thus Apoſtaſie hath been conſidered in the kind quality of it: Now in the next place we may ſee how it ſhews it ſelf in the degrees of it.</p>
                  <p>The Queſtion is, <hi>What are thoſe degrees and ſteps in which this Apoſtaſie doth ſhew it ſelf?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Apoſtaſie doth ſhew it ſelf in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of ſeveral Duties of Gods Worſhip, or of Family Duties, or private Chriſtian Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and at laſt in the neglect of the Publick Worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Apoſtaſie beginneth in ſecret, in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of ſecret Prayer, that which is called clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet Prayer, or praying alone, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. or in the neglect of ſelf examination; that which is called a judging a Mans ſelf. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31. to judge our ſtate whether it be happy or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, to judge our daily way and particular actions, whether they be good or evil, and to this is requiſite ſome convenient ſeaſon daily, and a Conſcience and Heart awakened to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the timely way of Self examination,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191877:12"/>
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6. And the neglect of theſe Duties is, either total, as thoſe who have caſt off ſecret Prayer, and Self-examination, and do neglect any ſet, ſolemn and ſteady atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to theſe duties, <hi>Job</hi> 15.9. unleſs it be in ſome fit of diſtreſs, and then they cry to God, and ſay, <hi>Ariſe and ſave us,</hi> Jer. 2.27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or if they do daily attend to theſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and yet neglect that which is of moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal and ſpecial concernment to their own Souls; you may be in a ſecret place with a Friend, and have much diſcourſe, and that in ſecret, and yet not one word of ſecret things, but that which any one may hear: likewiſe, you may be in prayer alone in ſecret, and yet not one word of that which is of moſt ſecret concernment to your Soul, but that which may be expreſt before a Family or a Congregation; and thus one principal end of Secret Prayer is loſt, which reſpecteth the Confeſſion of ſecret ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. and the petitioning for thoſe perſonal and ſecret favours which may not ſo conveniently be expreſt before others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.9. But the ſpecialty intended in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this, is to ſhew how far the neglect of theſe ſecret Duties doth argue a declenſion from Religion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Thoſe who neglect ſecret Duties have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191877:13"/>loſt one main evidence of ſincere worſhipping of God, not only becauſe they live in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of a known command of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.6. and not only becauſe they do decline from the uſual practice of the godly, who are wont to perform theſe ſecret duties daily morning and evening, and ſometimes thrice a day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. but how is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible theſe can have an evidence of ſincere worſhipping of God, ſeeing they attend no worſhip but what is before men, and therefore muſt be judged to act the part of a Hypocrite, ſo our Saviour Chriſt reaſoneth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe who neglect theſe ſecret Duties, have loſt the ſenſe of perſonal, inward Soul-difficulties; for whoſoever feels in a broken-hearted manner, his Soul pinched and preſs'd with difficulties, he muſt and will have an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let by ſecret Prayer, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.11. <hi>Behold he Prayeth,</hi> he embraceth Prayer not only as a duty, but as a gracious liberty; but amongſt his Soul difficulties, he ever finds ſome which cannot be ſo particularly and expediently reached but by ſecret Prayer, and calleth for a praying apart, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.14. but thoſe who neglect theſe ſecret duties are paſt feeling of theſe difficulties, and as they feel no ſuch need of ſecret prayer, ſo Chriſt paſſeth by them, as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:191877:13"/>thoſe who have no work for Chriſt to do for them in ſecret, and what will they do in that time, when <hi>Hezekiah</hi> like, they muſt turn their face towards the wall; and then if ſecret prayer be not the means to take the laſt ſtep right, they fall into the everlaſting pit, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 38.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Theſe have loſt the preſence of Chriſt in ſecret; and as they have forſaken him in ſecret, ſo he will forſake them openly. There are many are very deſirous to hold the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt openly, although they neglect his preſence in ſecret, but this cannot be, they have no promiſe and grounded hope of his preſence openly, who do neglect the means of his preſence in ſecret, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5. Apoſtaſie firſt beginneth in cloſets and ſecret places, and that which is in ſecret, evil in the ſight of God, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.9. and then behold greater, and more open abominations than theſe: And ſo we proceed to the Second.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A neglect of Family Duties; as Prayer in the Family morning and evening, and are of the number of thoſe Families which do not call upon the Name of God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25. or neglect reading the Word of God daily in the Family, or occaſional repeating of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or of that daily inſtructing the Family
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191877:14"/>by Catechiſing or other profitable means as is commanded, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7. and this neglect is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Either total and are under the ſame ſentence of wrath with the Heathen, and are heatheniſh Families, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or thoſe who are inconſtant in theſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties if prayer in the evening, yet none in the morning, or if prayer, yet have ſtrangely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got that by Word and Prayer all is ſanctified, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. but the ſpecialty I intend in this is not ſo much to prove theſe to be duties, for who knoweth not this, who knoweth any thing of the Word of God, and of the practice of godly Families; but let us conſider how far a neglect of theſe doth argue Apoſtacy from Religion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Theſe want true ſanctified love to their Families; the natural love doth incline them to take care and provide for their Families in things of concernment to the outward Man, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. Otherwiſe they are worſe than an Infidel, and if they had true ſanctified love to their families, this would make them as readily to take care for their Families in their Soul concernments, and <hi>Abraham</hi>-like as a head of the Family, to inſtruct, yea command an attendance to the great things of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. but theſe want natural affection truly ſanctified.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:191877:14"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe want love to God, and to their own Souls.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They want love to God, for this would diſpoſe them to a through care to bring up their Family in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They want love to their own Souls, its not poſſible for one to pitty his own Soul, but preſently he will pitty and take care of the Souls of others, eſpecially of thoſe who are nearly related to him: if a Maſter of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily be under a ſtrong impreſſion, and a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel melting working of a Spirit of love to his own Soul, <hi>Ephraim</hi>-like to bemoan himſelf, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18. he will then need no other motive to make him pray in his Family, Inſtruct, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, and uſe all poſſible means for the good of his Family.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Theſe want true love to Church and Common-wealth; they cannot but know that ſuch as Families are, ſuch at laſt the Church and Common-wealth muſt be. How can it be that a Maſter of Family, who liveth in neglect of Family Duties, ſhould prove a true Friend to the purity and power of Religion in Church, or to a true pious Government in the Common wealth? he that will not ſerve God in his own Houſe, will not be a true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:191877:15"/>of God in the houſe of the Lord, nor in the Common wealth, let us view well <hi>Joſhuah</hi>'s ſpeech and practice, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.15. and what <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2.</p>
                  <p>The third Particular followeth, and that is a neglect of private Chriſtian Meetings.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As thoſe ſet and ſolemn Meetings for Conference about the great things of God, and to pray together, and ſometimes adding Faſting and Prayer.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or thoſe occaſional Meetings of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, taking opportunities as they have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions one with another, to converſe about their Soul concerns.</p>
                  <p>And the neglect of theſe is either 1. Total; there are ſome who have wholly forſaken theſe Aſſembling of themſelves together: or 2. If they hold up ſome ſet Meetings; yet as to thoſe intimate Diſcourſes, by laying toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Obſervations of the times, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Soul-concerns, as thoſe Jewels ſpoken of in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. from theſe they are Strangers, and will give no heart-encouragement to other Chriſtians to come near to them, with intimate Conference about perſonal and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Experiences of the Lords dealing with them; and theſe know not what it meaneth to come into that broken hearted way of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:191877:15"/>one to another, their temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſnares, and Soul-hazards, and that which is called by the Apoſtle a confeſſing of Faults one to another, and a praying one for another, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16.</p>
                  <p>But the ſpecialty likewiſe we intend in this, is to ſhew how far theſe neglects do argue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Theſe neglect a principal means of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical communion of Chriſtians, that wherein much of the life of it doth conſiſt; for pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Chriſtian Communion cannot principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt in Apellations, and Titles, nor in meeting together at a Sacrament; but in caring one for another, as members of the ſame body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.25. bearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Burdens, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2. communicating one to another of ſpiritual gifts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.11, 12. but thoſe ſolemn Chriſtian Meetings or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional intimate Diſcourſes, whereby Chriſtians are intimately acquainted with one anothers Burdens, and Soul-concerns; theſe lead into the life of practical communion, and where theſe Chriſtian Meetings fail, their communion vaniſheth into Names, Titles, or ſome very powerleſs forms of communion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe do give place to many dangerous Temptations and diſtempers; for while they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:191877:16"/>live as Strangers from the Souls one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or any ſuch intimate Chriſtian Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences; the Tempter is at hand upon the leaſt occaſion, to come in with uncharitable ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and to imploy any evil In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rument to ſow ſeeds of diſcord amongſt Chriſtians, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20. and when theſe come to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ords Supper, the Goſpel Paſſeover, if they be not paſt ſeeling, they will find it too hard for them to eat with the unleavened Bread of Sincerity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. with that true Goſpel ſpirit of unity as becometh thoſe who eat of the ſame ſpiritual Bread, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. yea its uſually ſeen (through the Lords juſt judgement) that thoſe who are become Strangers from Chriſtian Meetings, or the hearty way of the management of them, that they are left to too much familiarity with other Companions to the reproach of their Profeſſion, and harm to their own Souls, and at laſt the wrath of God comes and finds them in fellowſhip with Children of Diſobedience in ſome works of darkneſs, which they ought to have reproved, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11.</p>
                  <p>The next Conſideration follows:</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>How Apoſtaſie doth ſhew it ſelf in the neglect of publick Worſhip?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> is, In neglect either of thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:191877:16"/>Ordinances which all are commanded to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, as publick Prayer, and hearing the Word of God Preached, and particularly of Sanctifying the Sabbath; Or a neglect of thoſe Ordinances which do properly belong to thoſe in Church Relation, and particularly in neglect of the Lords Supper and Church Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A neglect of thoſe publick Ordinances which all are commanded to attend, as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayer, and hearing the Word preached, and this neglect is, either.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Upon ſome unneceſſary occaſions, not works of Mercy, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.13. but from an unwillingneſs to break throng any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble difficulty, or to beat coſt about publick Worſhip not as <hi>David,</hi> who would not offer that to the Lord which coſt nothing. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or not careful to come ſeaſonably to the publick Worſhip, as before the firſt Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or entrance be made into the publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; in theſe they are careleſs, not as thoſe in <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s time, who were ſeaſonably ready, and waited for the publick Worſhip of God, <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.1.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or attending upon the Ordinances in a ſlighty and ſleepy manner, not offering their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191877:17"/>Bodies as a living Sacrifice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Haſtening a way upon unneceſſary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions before the laſt Prayer be ended, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Bleſſing be diſpenſed, not as thoſe who went not away before the Name of the Lord was put upon them, in a way of bleſſing by the Lords Meſſenger, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.26, 27. More particularly this neglect doth ſhew it ſelf and Apoſtaſie therein, in the neglect of Sanctifying the Sabbath; and that is either,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In neglecting to prepare for the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath by a timely breaking off from worldly Occaſions, but do run on to the very time of the beginning of the Sabbath, to that in their Worldly concerns, their foot ſteppeth into the time of the Sabbath, or ſo nigh to it that they cannot prepare for holy time, and the Duties of the ſame ſo ſuddenly, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or in the time of the Sabbath, a neglect to Sanctifie the Holy time, having forgot to practice that which is ſo plainly declared: Call the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord, and honourable, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine own wayes, not finding thine own pleaſure, not ſpeaking thine own words, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As ſoon as the Sabbath is ended, thoſe who do fall into vain and unprofitable diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:191877:17"/>which at all times are ſinful, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.4. but in a Sabbath Evening are the Soul robbing temptations, by which Satan does bereave them of all the good they have ſeen or heard of God in the holy Day, or are running into their worldly Diſcourſes, as if they were glad the Sabbath were ended, <hi>Ames</hi> 8.5.</p>
                  <p>But let us likewiſe in this conſider how far theſe neglects do argue a declenſion from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Theſe who do neglect the publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and particularly the Sabbath, do fall ſhort of that Religiouſneſs which many Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and meer Formaliſts do attain, for theſe in the publick Worſhip of God, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves as the Lords People are wont to do, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31, 32. <hi>Many have the form of Religion and not the power,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. <hi>Many have the letter of Worſhip and not the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 2.28. but thoſe who have not the form, the letter, and external part of worſhip are far off from the power, the ſpirit and inward worſhipping of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe do by their practice ſay, that the worſhip of God is a burden, and an abhorring to them, their loathneſs to come to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, their weariſome Behaviour in the time of it, and their haſtening from it do
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:191877:18"/>teſtifie to their faces, that the Sabbath, and the Word of the Lord is a burden to them, and theſe are a burden to the Lord, and he threatens to forget them, to forſake them, and to caſt them out of his preſence, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.39.40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.27. theſe by their works do ſay, their Souls have abhorred God; and the Lord he ſaith he hath abhorred them, and that he will not feed them; but that which dieth let it die, and let the reſt eat the fleſh one of another, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.8, 9.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond follows, and that is the neglect of thoſe Ordinances which do properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to thoſe in Church Relation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A neglect of preparing for, and of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take hold of the Covenant, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.4.5 not as thoſe whoſe faces are Zionward, and weeping they will go to ſeek the Lord, and joyn themſelves in a perpetual Covenant ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be forgotten, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.4, 5. but thoſe who turn their backs upon the viſible Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the adminiſtrations of it, do by their practice diſown God, and ſay, the true God is not their God; for how can God be their God, but by Covenant; and what is the Church Covenant, but an Adminiſtration of the Covenant of Grace: and that Soul who doth by words or works, by opinion or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191877:18"/>turn away from the Covenant, by negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to prepare for it, or take hold of it, is a ſtranger from the Covenant, and liveth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. and if by his Parentage and Birth, he is in viſible Covenant, and when grown up, yet doeth neglect to look after it, or take hold of it, he doth by his practiſe deſpiſe his Birth right; and the time may come when he may ſeek for a Bleſſing with tears, and yet find no place of Repentance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or thoſe who neglect the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and can content themſelves to be Baptized, or to have their Children Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, but are inſenſible of the need of the Lords Supper, that great Seal of Communion with Chriſt and his Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17. or that haſtening to this great Ordinance without due and that worthy preparation in the way of ſelf-examination, and diſcerning the Lords body, <hi>and theſe do eat and drink their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.29. and if the Church doth admit thoſe to the Lords Table who are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly unworthy, they will provoke the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> did, that for this cauſe many amongſt them were weak, and many ſickly, and ſome were taken away by death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:191877:19"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Or thoſe who in their Church Relation do live in the neglect of Church Diſcipline, that is, they give offence but will not give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisſaction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23. or they will take offence but not manage it according to Chriſts Order, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.19. and whatever their goodly words are, yet they are but as a Hind let looſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.21. and their works ſay, they will not have Chriſt to rule over them; and the quarrel the Lord hath againſt theſe &amp; the al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rementioned, is that which is called the quarrel of his Covenant, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.25. a moſt ſearful quarrel. And to conclude this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, we may conſider,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some do deſpiſe the Covenant in the adminiſtrations of it, or by their practice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that the Covenant is not worthy of their care labour and coſt, and it may be drop ſome ſcoff or mocking expreſſion, but will not ſeek the Lord in the way of his Covenant, theſe are in the high way to that unpardonable ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, of counting the blood of the Covenant an unholy thing, and of doing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite to the ſpirit of Grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.27, 28.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some have viſibly taken hold of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant but do live in the breach of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.37, 38. &amp; 50.16, 17. and the Lord ſaith, what haſt thou to do to take my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:191877:19"/>into thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and caſteſt my words behind thee. And the quarrel the Lord hath againſt a People or particular perſons, whether it be for deſpiſing his Covenant or breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ever implieth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Theſe are guilty of ſinning againſt the greateſt love; for the love of God in conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to enter into Covenant with a ſinner, is the higheſt act of love, and to deſpiſe this Covenant or the things of it, or live in the breach of it, is to ſpit reproach and contempt in the moſt beautiful face of divine Love: do you thus require the Lord, O fooliſh People and unwiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe ſin againſt the only Remedy. What cure and relief can there be for ſinners but from Chriſt, and how doth Chriſt relieve but in the way of his Covenant, in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it: how can thoſe eſcape who neglect this great Salvation? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. and hence follows the greateſt puniſhment for the quarrel of the Covenant, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.3. You I have known of all the Families of the Earth, and you I will puniſh, when the inquiry is made when they ſee what plagues &amp; ſickneſſes come upon the Land, wherefore hath the Lord done thus to this Land? and the Anſwer is, becauſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:191877:20"/>they have forſaken the Covenant of the Lord God of their Fathers, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.23, 24, 25. and thus we ſee how Apoſtaſie doth ſhew it ſelf in the degrees of it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How gradual it is: <hi>Firſt,</hi> A growing cold in ſecret Duties, then remiſs and formal in Family duties, and at length ſlighty and cold in communion with Saints, in private and publick Ordinances, and at laſt twice dead and pulled up by the roots, <hi>Jude</hi> 12. they were dead as to a principle of ſpiritual life, as all are by nature, and they are dead as to the life and zeal of viſible Profeſſion which they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times had.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As theſe declenſions are gradual, ſo they grow on upon an Apoſtatizing people inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, at firſt ſomewhat afraid and ſtartled, but by a cuſtomary declenſion grow inſenſible of the danger, and ſo ready to heal themſelves with lazy deſires, and pretended good mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and formal covenantings, until at laſt they are left to a good opinion of their ſtate, that they ſay, Wherein ſhall they return? as if they were not convinced; although from the dayes of their Fathers, they had gone away from the Ordinances of the Lord and not kept them in that purity and power, as they were left to them by their Fathers, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Jer,</hi> 8.5, 6.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:191877:20"/>
                  <p>In the next place follows the conſideration of the bitter fruits of Apoſtaſie, as they are ſpecified in the advertiſement of our Rulers; and for the clearing the particulars, let us eſpecially obſerve how it comes to paſs that a People living under the means of Grace are left to thoſe abominations: and the Queſtion in the firſt place is,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How it comes to paſs that ſome living under the means of grace are left to groſs Ignorance or abuſe of their light and knowledge?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe ſome under the means of Grace have rejected the knowledge of God, and therefore are left to groſs ignorance, or not loving truth as truth, and therefore are left to abuſe their light and knowledge to their deſtruction.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some have rejected knowledge, that its become the object of their hatred, as if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction was not worthy of their love, and if they be reproved, they do deſpiſe reproof, and the reprover, and will not obey the voice of their Teachers, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.12, 13. the reading good Books, the Writing and Repeating of Sermons, the Schools of Learning, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with the wiſe; and all good means of knowledge in their hearts they deſpiſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22, <hi>How long ye ſimple ones will ye love ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:191877:21"/>and ſcorners delight in ſcorning, and fools hate knowledge,</hi> Prov. 1.22.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The puniſhment upon theſe followeth, therefore they are left to a ſottiſh ignorance, they have not ſo much light as ſhall keep them from ſottiſh and bruitiſh ignorance, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.22. they are ſottiſh Children, they have no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.4. ſurely they are poor and fooliſh, they know not the way of the Lord, and the judgement of their God, they have rejected the knowledge of God, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore left to the darkneſs of groſs Ignorance.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond ſort are thoſe upon whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences the light hath ſhined, but have not loved truth as truth, theſe have knowledge and will be ſearching and proving excellent things, and having a form of knowledge, may be guids to the blind, and hold forth light to thoſe who are in darkneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.18, 19, 20. and theſe love to live under an able Miniſtry, and will uphold Schools of Leaaning, and be in the uſe of all means of knowledge, but yet never did receive the love of the truth, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. the truth it ſelf, and the true knowledge of it, was never the ultimate and principal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their love, but only a mediate object, that by means of their light and knowledge, they ſet up advance and ſerve ſome Idol in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:191877:21"/>their hearts, but do not like to retian to God in knowledge as its the knowledge of God, Rom. 1.28.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The puniſhment upon theſe is, therefore they are left to abuſe their light and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to their deſtruction, either to pride and vain glory, their knowledge hath puffed them up, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. or they are by means of their light become the more ſubtile to deviſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts for ſin, and the more ſlye in oppoſing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly the life and power of Godlineſs, the more crafty to deceive others and to cheat their own Souls, the more wiſe to do evil but to do good they have no knowledge and are blinded at laſt with ſelf conceitedneſs, and ſay the Law of the Lord is with them, but they have rejected the Word of the Lord, and what wiſdome is in them. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.8, 9.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some truths of greateſt concernment to them they ſhall not ſee, but groap for light at noon day as if it were night, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.29. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe Truths which they do ſee, yet they ſhall be left to miſapply, pervert, and wreſt to their deſtruction, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.10, 11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thoſe Truths which they do apply rightly, yet their hearts ſhall not be affected with them, and not be reformed by them, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:191877:22"/>to them, it ſhall be as if they knew nothing, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.8, 9. theſe have often perverted their underſtanding and abuſed their knowledge, and their underſtanding and knowledge ſhall pervert and miſlead them, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 47.10.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond follows concerning Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How it comes to paſs that ſome under the means of Grace are givtn up to Prophaneneſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> is, Becauſe ſome under the means of Grace have rejected ſaving Grace in the Goſpel, and therefore the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws common reſtraining Grace from them, and they become prophane.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some are prophane, although they live under the means of Grace, theſe will not ſhew a civil reſpect to Religion and that good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which civility will teach; their words are ſcornful and mocking, abuſing the Holy Scriptures in a jeſting and deriding manner, like thoſe Scoffers who ſaid, where is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his coming? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. theſe are a peſt and a moſt dangerous infection in ſocieties, by their evil communication do cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, Geſtures and Lives do declare them to be like a mocking <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> or prophane <hi>Eſau, Heb.</hi> 12.15, 16. look diligently leſt any
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:191877:22"/>man fail of the Grace of God leſt there be any Fornicator or Prophane Perſon as <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe have rejected ſaving Grace in the Goſpel, the God of all Grace by the means of his Grace, the Ordinances, and by the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Examples of the godly, ſeconded by ſome afflicting providences, and ſometimes with convictions and terrors of Conſcience hath been ſtriving with theſe, but they would not hearken to his voice, and would have none of him and his ſaving Grace, and therefore are given up to their hearts luſts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11, 12. <hi>Wo unto thee, wilt thou not be clean, when will it once be,</hi> Jer. 13.27.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Hence the Lord hath withdrawn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining Grace, that thoſe who reject ſaving Grace in the Goſpel, and will not live as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh godly men; the Lord withdraws common reſtraining Grace from them, that they ſhall not live as becometh men, this is the reaſon why ſome are ſo lewdly filthy, that in their filthineſs is lewdneſs, becauſe they would not be purged, and therefore the Lord ſaith, they ſhall not be purged, but the Lords fury ſhall reſt upon them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. this is the reaſon why ſome under the means of Grace are more prophane than ſome others who
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:191877:23"/>enjoy no ſuch means to reform them, and that they are become more prophane then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enjoyed the means of Grace; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have provoked the Lord by their reſiſtings of the ſtrivings of the Spirit of Grace, to give them up to moſt horrid and helliſh prophanenſs, that as <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall exceed the filth of <hi>Samaria</hi> and <hi>Sodom,</hi> Ezek. 16.51. and of this bitter fruit of Apoſtaſie: that Man of God of moſt bleſſed memory, Mr: <hi>Thomas Hooker,</hi> was wont fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to warn <hi>New-England,</hi> ſaying, do you wonder that ſome in <hi>New-England</hi> are left to ſuch abominations, I tell you that ſome in <hi>New-England</hi> will be given up to greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs. His Sermons upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11, 12 and <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28. do at large declare this.</p>
                  <p>The third bitter fruit, concerning groſs neglects of relative Duties: And the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why are ſome under the means of Grace left to thoſe palpable neglects of relative Duties, in Family, Church and Common-Wealth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwer:</hi> Becauſe ſome under the means of Grace, living in neglect of Duties towards God, and of duties towards others in the Lord, its juſt with the Lord to leave them to groſs neglects of relative duties one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:191877:23"/>
                  <p n="1">1. There are ſome who though they enjoy the means of Grace, yet they live in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of duties in Relation to the God of Grace, he hath profered a holy Marriage Covenant to them; and himſelf as the only ſuitable March and Husband for the immortal Soul, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.5. but they have loved Strangers and after them they will go, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.25. neither will they honour him as a Father, nor fear him as their Maſter, but deſpiſe his Name, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. if they call him their God, yet they caſt off the thing that is good, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.2.5</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hence it follows, theſe never did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form duties in relation to others in the Lord, for this is the Religious and true Goſpel band in all Relations; <hi>Husbands love your Wives, as Chriſt loved his Church,</hi> Eph. 5.25. <hi>Wives ſubmit your ſelves to your Husbands, as is fit in the Lord,</hi> Col. 3.18. <hi>Children obey your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the Lord,</hi> Epheſ. 6.1. <hi>Servants obey your Maſters in ſingleneſs of heart, fearing the Lord,</hi> Col. 3.22. But thoſe who do not conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiouſly attend duties in Relation to the Lord, do feel no ſuch Religious band upon their hearts and Conſciences in relation to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but act only as moved by ſome natural or moral Principles which are too weak to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the violence of temptations and diſtempers.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:191877:24"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Therefore its juſt with the Lord to leave theſe to ſome notorious neglects of relative duties one to another; if the Husband be a man of <hi>Belial,</hi> he is likewiſe a <hi>Nabal,</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is with him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.25. and will behave himſelf fooliſhly or bitterly againſt the Wife of his Boſome, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.19. If the Wife doeth not ſubject to her Husband in the Lord, as the Church is ſubject to Chriſt, ſhe will be left to act the part of a <hi>Zipporah,</hi> in a reproachful manner to her Husband, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5 24. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.25. If Parents, and Heads of Families do neglect obedience unto and to act in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Heavenly Father, and live as if they had no Maſter in Heaven, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9. they will be left either by their raſh paſſions to provoke unto wrath, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9. and to diſcourage thoſe under their Government, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.21. or they will by an unadviſed indulgence neglect to bring theirs up in the nurture and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4. but let them live like the wild Aſs in the Wilderneſs, ſnuffing up the Wind, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.24. and if Children are not in ſubjection to the Father of Spirits, they will not behave themſelves reverently to the Fathers of their fleſh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. They do not fear God the ancient of dayes, and they will behave themſelves proudly againſt the Aged,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:191877:24"/>the baſe againſt the Honourable, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.5.</p>
                  <p>The like may be ſaid of neglect of duties in a Plantation, Church and Common-wealth-Relations, if Rulers Civil or Eccleſiaſtick do not rule actually in the fear of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3. they will either tolerate intolerable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and not care for thoſe things, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.17. or they will lade Men with burdens grievous to be born, but they themſelves will not touch the burden, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.46. and will turn Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Wormwood, <hi>Amos.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                  <p>And if a people do not ſubject to Rulers for the Lords ſake, they will either pervert Orders, and wreſt Laws to the bringing in of Diſorder, and ſet up corrupt Rulers, thoſe of whom the Lord ſaith, he knew them not, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.3. and like People at laſt like Prieſt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9. or they will deſpiſe Dominions, <hi>Jude</hi> 8. and behave themſelves as Thorns that the man that ſhall touch them, muſt be ſenced with iron, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.6.</p>
                  <p>The third bitter fruit of Apoſtaſie is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How is Contentiouſneſs a bitter fruit of Apoſtaſie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe thoſe who have turned from the right way of true peace with God, and their own Conſciences are given up to thoſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:191877:25"/>contentious Principles and Practices, which ſhall break their peace with others.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is the right way of true peace with God, and with our own Conſciences, namely to abhor every known ſin, to deny our ſelves, to mortifie Pride, Envy, Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and all ſelf humoring Luſts, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.1, and in this right way of peace to take hold of the ſtrength of God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 27.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.79.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe who turn from this right way of true peace with God, are given up to Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs, the things of their peace are hidden from their eyes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42. there is no judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their goings, they have made to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves crooked paths, and they ſhall not know peace, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59.8. 1. Thoſe who ſtrive againſt their Maker, and ſet Briars and Thorns in Battel againſt God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 27.4. its no wonder if the beſt of them be as a Briar, and the moſt upright of them be as a Thorn-hedge, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe who will not deny themſelves for the ſake of true peace with God and their own Conſciences, let it not ſeem ſtrange if they will not deny themſelves to pleaſe others in that which is good, and would be to edification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.27.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:191877:25"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Thoſe who have vexed the Holy Spirit of God, by their Rebellion or Unfaithfulneſs, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.10. they will grieve others by their giving offence, or raſhly taking up of offences, or contentious manner of managing offences, and will make diviſions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Thoſe who never had the ſenſe of the ſweetneſs of true peace with God and their Conſciences, cannot in a right Goſpel ſenſe be kind and tender-hearted, ready to forgive as God for Chriſts ſake forgiveth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32. Theſe have broken the ſtaff of beauty; and the ſtaff of Bands and Brother-hood ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be broken, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.10, 14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Thoſe who have been wonted to flatter their own Souls with a falſe peace, and to heal the hurts of their Conſciences ſlightly, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.14. and would not endure the faithful wounds of a Friend, by ſearching reproofs; theſe will ſpeak peaceably to a neighbour, and yet their hearts lie in wait, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.8. the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this is, that fire of Diviſions which conſumeth their peace with Neigbours did firſt begin in the fire of Gods wrath, becauſe of ſome grievous provocation againſt God, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.20, 21. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 4.21.</p>
                  <p>The fourth bitter Fruit is Senſuality.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:191877:26"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How is Senſuality a bitter fruit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe thoſe who have deſpiſed the things of the Spirit of God, the only objects of Spiritual ſenſes, are given up to pleaſe their ſenſual Luſts by Objects ſuitable to the carnal ſenſes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There are the things of the Spirit of God, thoſe Graces of the Spirit in and by the means of Grace communicated; Love, Peace, Joy, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs. Temperance, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. and theſe are the Objects of the ſpiritual ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear what the Spirit ſaith, is only by a ſpiritual ſenſe of hearing. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. to ſee the things of the Spirit, is only by a ſpiritual ſenſa of ſeeing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. and to taſt the things of the Spirit is requiſite a ſpiritual ſenſe of taſting. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 34 8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But thoſe who have deſpiſed the things of the Spirit are given up to their ſenſual luſts, theſe are ſenſual and have not the ſpirit, <hi>Jude</hi> 19. they have taken more pleaſure to hear a vain ſong or the noiſe of a Fiddle, then to hear the bleſſed ſound of <hi>Emmanuel</hi>'s voice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.15. they take more delight to behold vanity then to ſee the beauty of the Lord in his Houſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. theſe take more pleaſure
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:191877:26"/>to pleaſe their appetite with meat and drink, and to content other ſenſual luſts, then to feed upon the fleſh, and drink the blood of the Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 6.56. <hi>and the feaſt of fat things, and wine of the Lees,</hi> and thoſe Goſpel dainties are deſpiſed. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25.6.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Hence they are given up to ſenſual Luſts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Sometimes to exceſſive Drinking, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.18. and ſometimes to laſciviouſneſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They commonly do walk at the utmoſt bounds of liberty, and abuſe their Liberties unto carnal libertiniſm, and ſenſual licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Take theſe at their beſt, the ſavour they have of the Goſpel and of ſome common gifts of the Spirit, is no better than a ſavour of Death unto Death, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. for they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the things of the fleſh as more pleaſant then the things of the ſpirit, and love pleaſures more than God, 2 <hi>Tim,</hi> 3, 4. and do only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour thoſe common gifts of the ſpirit which they can receive and abuſe unto carnal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior purpoſes and ends.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And Hence it is that ſome do expend more upon their ſenſual luſts, than to uphold the work of Chriſt in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:191877:27"/>wealth, and are more in debt annually in the Ordinary keepers Book for ſtrong Drink, than in the Town &amp; Countrey Rate, theſe have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared their Corn, their Flax, and their Wool for their ſenſual luſts, as ſometimes they did for <hi>Baal, Hoſ.</hi> 2.8, 9. and the Lord threatens to take away their Corn, and Flax, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the ſeaſon of them.</p>
                  <p>The fifth bitter Fruit of Apoſtaſie is Pride.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>How is Pride a bitter Fruit of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe thoſe who will not ſeek the praiſe which is of God by a humble walking, are given up to ſeek the praiſe which is of men by lifting up themſelves by ſome vain glorious means.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We ought to ſeek the praiſe which is of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. and this by a humble walking, which is alwayes in every ſtate good, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe who will not ſeek the praiſe which is of God, are given up to ſeek the praiſe which is of men; for they love the praiſe which is of men more than the praiſe which is of God. <hi>John</hi> 12.43. and this their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth ſhew it ſelf in lifting up themſelves by ſome vain-glorious means, in which we may conſider.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:191877:27"/>
                  <p n="1">1. The lifting up: 1. In reſpect of Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, contemning them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.9. and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times oppreſſing them, abuſing of power and greatneſs to the wronging of Inferiours, as great Fiſhes devour the leſſer, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13, 14. but their Pride will not ſuffer them to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to thoſe who are of low degree, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16. except it be <hi>Abſalom</hi> like, to humble themſelves at a turn, that they may exalt themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In reſpect of Equals, aſpiring after a firſtneſs and honour above thoſe unto whom honour is due equal with themſelues, but thoſe who are firſt ſhall be laſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In reſpect of Superiors; Pride ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is not aſhamed to ſhew it ſelf, in lifting up the Proud above a Superior; yea, to caſt down a Superiour, that by his fall the Proud may exalt himſelf, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.5. this is like <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi>'s lifting himſelf up above, and againſt his Father.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The means by which the Proud do uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally lift up themſelves, are vain-glorious.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In aſpiring after ſome priviledge above others, ſome freedome from a burden, that they may be eaſed, and let others be burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13, 14. affecting ſome precedency and preheminence above others, when no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:191877:28"/>reaſon can be given for it, but only they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a high conceit of ſome ſuppoſed worth in themſelves, and therefore love the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.8. but if they ſought the praiſe which is of God, by a humble walking, this would teach them in lowlineſs of mind to ſerve God, and to eſteem others better than themſelves, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A ſecond vain-glorious means by which the proud doth lift up himſelf, is ſome ſign or badge of honour.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some Title of Honour which hath a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry pleaſant ſound in an ambitious ear, to be called Maſter, or to have ſome chief place in places of Meetings, otherwiſe he doth not ſit eaſie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.6, 10. Many inſtances may be given to ſhew how Pride the firſt born of the Devil is fruitful, but the jettings, and vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Pride in many in their Apparel is ſo manifeſt, that the humble are grieved to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, and the proud themſelves are vexed with envy, to ſee ſo many equally lifting up themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That ſtrange affectation of being firſt and forward, and of being furtheſt and moſt in a new &amp; ſtrange Faſhion, for which the Lord threatned to puniſh the Kings Children, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:191877:28"/>
                  <p n="2">2. An affecting of ſuch Apparel as ſhall make them ſeem to be of a higher rank than they are, ſo that no diſtinction of the ranks and degrees can be diſcerned by their Apparel; none between Rich and Poor, Ruler and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Maſter and Servant, Miſtriſs and Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid; theſe by their Apparel do ſhew that parity is pleaſing to their Pride.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Theſe ſpend ſo much upon Apparel that either they waſt their Eſtate, or lie in Debt, or pinch their Bellies of neceſſaries, that they might adorn and deck themſelves with the or, naments of Pride.</p>
                  <p>But the reaſon of the ventings of Pride in theſe and in many other wayes, is becauſe theſe have not a high eſteem of Humility, as the precious cloathing, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5. and of a meek and quiet Spirit, as more worth than Cloth of Gold, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. but they have deſpiſed the humble walker, and called the proud happy, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.15. and therefore though they have often heard of the evil of this ſin, and known ſomething of the fearful events of it upon ſome, yet <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>-like are hardened in their Pride, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.22. their pride hath ſtop'd their ears that they will not hear, and ſhut their eyes that they will not ſee, and although their dangerous ſlippings and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:191877:29"/>Stumblings upon the dark Mountains, while they wander in their Pride, are manifeſt; yet they will haſten towards the top of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain until they be caſt down head-long, and leave others to mourn in ſecret places for their pride, becauſe they will not hear, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.16, 17.</p>
                  <p>The ſixth bitter fruit of Apoſtaſie.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs a bitter fruit of Apoſtaſie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe thoſe who have deſpiſed the true riches, and eſteemed gain to be godlineſs, are therefore left to ſeek worldly Wealth by unrighteous means.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is the true riches, Chriſt the Pearl of price, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.46. the graces of his Spirit, to be rich in Faith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. a meek and a quiet Spirit of great price, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wiſdom more precious than the Rubies, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.15. to lay up treaſure in Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.20. by a true godly converſation: for godlineſs with contentment is great gain, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But the unrighteous have deſpiſed the true Riches, they are not rich towards God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.21. and gain is their Godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. they will have and hold ſuch, and ſo much of Godlineſs, as may be ſerviceable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:191877:29"/>to or conſiſtent with their worldly gain, and behave themſelves as <hi>Demas</hi> who had forſaken <hi>Paul,</hi> and loved this preſent World, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Hence it is that theſe are left to ſeek Worldly wealth by unrighteous means; they will be rich, and if they cannot compaſs it by juſt means, they will get it by unjuſt means, although at the end they are befooled to their everlaſting confuſion. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. But the reaſon why they are left to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, is their love to money, which is the root of all evil, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. and they having undervalued and deſpiſed the true ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, are given up to overvalue and idolize Worldly wealth; and hence followeth ſuch deceit, a ſelling truth for gain, and lying to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In Bargainings: ſtriving to defraud and go beyond another, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. and to deviſe all cunning evaſions to winde away from the equal ſcope of a Bargain, and will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it faithfully, without unjuſt vexing and damnifying another. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.2, 4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In Wares; Merchandize and Trading, a gaining what they can poſſibly, as if Juſtice had ſet them no bounds, but to gain what they can is their profeſſed juſtice; and their gain
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:191877:30"/>is their godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In Wages; impoveriſhing him who hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and their great deſign in taking work by the great (as they call it) is that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more Wages than their labour is worth; but their Money is put into a Bag with holes, <hi>Haggai</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In Treſpaſſings; they are not conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly careful to prevent damages, and when they know they have damnified a Neighbour, yet if they can they will hide it, and what they cannot hide, yet they will not freely and fully make ſatisfaction, ſo that their Neighbour can not dwell ſafely by them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.29.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In Debts; they will engage that which they know they cannot perform in an ordinary way, and when they have promiſed, they are not conſcientiouſly careful to perform their promiſe according to the true and equal ſcope of it, and that which is due, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.27, 28. but all theſe and many other unrighteous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices do proceed through the Lords juſt judgment, from a being empty and void of ſincere Love to God, and thoſe moſt rich and precious things of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are given up to an immoderate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate love of deceivable Riches, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are left to hold the truth in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:191877:30"/>and to be filled with all unrighteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 18.28, 29.</p>
                  <p>And what is the horrible event of this and all the former vices and bitter fruits of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe of theſe vile Examples, the Heathen do Blaſpheme the Name of our God, and are hardened in their Heatheniſh abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When the Heathen do behold thoſe who do profeſs to know God, and yet do live in prophareneſs, ſenſuality, contentiouſneſs, pride, unrighteouſneſs, therefore they blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the Name of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our words be concerning God, and our Religion; but the Heathen will judge &amp; ſpeak of our Religion, and the things of our God according as they ſee our works are.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hence the Heathen grow hardened <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their heatheniſh abominations, and are ready to think and ſay, they do well to run into all manner of prophaneneſs, ſeeing they behold ſuch vile examples in thoſe who do profeſs to know the true and great God, and eſpecially they grow hardened, and abound in that ſin of Drunkenneſs, ſeeing for the ſake of lucre many will ſell them ſtrong drink:</p>
                  <p>But the abominable practiſe of thoſe who
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:191877:31"/>are guilty of this, doth teſtifie againſt them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That they are far off from endeavouring by good works to convince and convert the Heathen, ſeeing for the ſake of worldly gain, they will feed their Luſts to the ruine of the wealth, health, and Souls of Heathen, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11, 12. Theſe are Taverns and Ordinary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers for Heathens luſts.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe love their gain more than their Neighbours, or their own ſafety, ſeeing they cannot but know, that many Outrages, yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Murthers have been committed by Drunken Indians in their Drunken poſture, and ſometimes in the Families of thoſe who have ſold them ſtrong Drink: or at leaſt the hazard is great.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Theſe love worldly gain more than God and their own Souls happineſs, for if they had love to God and to their own Souls good, they would practically intend the glory of God in all they do, and give no occaſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> nor to the Church of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31, 32. but if theſe who thus practiſe had any uſe of their Conſciences, as a witneſs or judge, their conſciences would tell them, that while they ſell ſtrong Drink to thoſe whom they know will abuſe it to Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, and in this, act contrary to to the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:191877:31"/>ſaw of the Common wealth, founded upon moral and religious Principles, and yet in this to intend Gods glory, is as far off from the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-intention of theſe Heathen Taverners, and as contrary to their practice, as Heaven and Hell are contrary one to the other.</p>
                  <p>And how juſt it is with the Lord that the Heathen ſhould be the rod of his anger to puniſh theſe crying abominations. The ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Amunition was for many years prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, but ſome for gain would ſecretly ſell Guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Heathen, and at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed to make the Law of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of none effect; and ſince that time <hi>New-England</hi> knows by woful experience the difference between fighting with <hi>Indians</hi> arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Guns, and thoſe who had only Bowes and Arrows. But the ſelling of ſtrong Drink to the <hi>Indians</hi> hath by ſtrict Laws frequently revived been prohibited, and yet how incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibly ſome do proceed is very manifeſt, and ſince the Wars, more abounding: And will not the Lord avenge himſelf of theſe for their Provocations, and provoke them with a fooliſh Nation, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.21. If our Rulers grow weary of puniſhing this horrible pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, the Lord God of Gods will begin to puniſh it after another manner, and make theſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:191877:32"/>who are guilty, to know that it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God, when his time is come to take vengeance for the deſpiſing of Moral Laws, and the ſtrivings of his Spirit of Grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31, 32.</p>
                  <p>Thus of Apoſtaſie conſidered in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Degrees, and bitter Fruits of the ſame, but before we come to the concluſion of theſe Diſcourſes; let us conſider,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>How it doth appear that the judgements come upon</hi> New-England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>are becauſe of the ſins of</hi> New-England, <hi>and not for probation or any other cauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe <hi>New-England</hi> found guilty of thoſe very ſins, for which the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments come upon them, are threatned by the Word of God: and therefore we muſt confeſs that what God hath ſpoken againſt us by his Holy Word, he hath inflicted upon us by his righteous hand.</p>
                  <p>And for the Clearing of this, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the judgements come upon <hi>New-England,</hi> are thoſe which are threatned by the Word of God, are manifeſt to all. Who knows not the mortal ſickneſſes, the withering bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, the Drought and the Sword to avenge the quarrel of the Covenant threatned in <hi>Lev.</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:191877:32"/>the 26. the 28. of <hi>Deuteronomie?</hi> and in many other places of Scripture, and none can be ignorant, that the Lord hath by his righteous hand executed theſe threatnings upon us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be thoſe who are more ſenſeleſs, then the Stork, the Turtle and the Swallow, who know their appointed times, and obſerve the time of their coming, <hi>but my People</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>know not the judgment of the Lord, Jer.</hi> 8.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That theſe judgements are come upon <hi>New-England;</hi> for the ſins of <hi>New-England</hi> will appear if we conſider negatively.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That theſe judgements are come not for probation only, nor principally, for God is not wont to inflict publick judgements upon a people for trial, although he doth ſometimes ſend affliction upon an upright <hi>Job</hi> for trial chiefly, and when affliction cometh for proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and trial principally it will appear upon examination, that the perſon afflicted is found walking in his uprightneſs before God, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.8, 12. and in the night of affliction, there ſhall be nothing found againſt this afflicted Saint but that which is conſiſtent with uprightneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.3. but who is able to make this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence for <hi>New-England,</hi> as to the generality of them, and as for thoſe who are called the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:191877:33"/>upright, what their innocency is, and what their guilt is; this will appear in that which is in the place of it, ſpoken concerning the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers manners and ſorts of guilt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Neither did <hi>New England</hi> in the ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of the Wars, ſuffer as witneſſes for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſake, although ſo far as the Antichriſtian Malice of ſome might be ſtirring up and working in and with the rage of the Heathen, and might by the provocations of <hi>New En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> againſt the Lord, take occaſion to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that of Chriſt and the Chriſtian Religion, which yet remained in the Churches of Chriſt in the Wilderneſs; in this reſpect Meat came out of the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er to the godly of the Land, and they might ſay as that holy Martyr <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> ſaid, It is not the condemnation of <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> ſimply intended by the Adverſary, but Chriſt and Truth, and <hi>Bradford</hi> is nothing but an inſtrument in which Chriſt and Truth is condemned and perſecuted by the Adverſary; and in this reſpect the Lord ſaith, and hath, and will do for his People, as ſometimes he ſaid by the Prophet, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.15. <hi>I am very ſore diſpleaſed with the Heathen, for I was a little diſpleaſed, and they helped forward their affliction:</hi> But yet our ſins muſt be confeſſed to be the Traitors, which gave the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:191877:33"/>into the hands of our Enemies againſt us, and the Lord ſaid of us; as ſometimes of that People, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.24. <hi>Who gave Jacob to the ſpoil, and Iſrael to the Robbers, did not the Lord, be againſt whom we have ſinned?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the next place Affirmatively, concerning the cauſes of the Judgements upon <hi>New-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> that <hi>New-England</hi> is found guilty of thoſe very ſins mentioned in the writing of our Rulers, and that theſe are the cauſes of thoſe judgements, will be made moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, if we conſider the divers manners and wayes by which a People are involved in guilt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some are guilty by actual Commiſſion, and that is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Either openly after the manner of the Prophane ſort, whoſe Countenance doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt them, and they declare their ſin as <hi>Sodom,</hi> they hide it not, wo unto their Soul, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or ſecretly, and ſometimes God doth inflict publick Judgements upon a People for ſecret ſins, and that is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When they are ſuch ſins as are not in the nature and kind of themſecret, but as they are by the tranſgreſſor bound up, and hiden by ſome deceiving Excuſes, and fallacious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:191877:34"/>
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.12. and the ignorance theſe pretend is wilful, and they are condemned by the Lord for willing ignorance, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or ſuch ſecret ſins as go before the open ſins, and the others do follow them, and together do provoke the Lord, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.9. and cannot be hid, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.25. both theſe openly or ſecretly are guilty of provocations by actual Commiſſion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some are guilty by way of approbation, by conſenting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.18. or countenancing, and thus <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi>'s love unto, and helping of ungodly <hi>Ahab,</hi> did provoke the Lord to wrath againſt him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Some are guilty by way of toleration, and thus <hi>Solomon</hi> did provoke the Lord to wrath by his tolerating of the Idolatry of his Wives, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Some are guilty by their omiſſion and neglect of means.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To prevent the provocations, and thus ſome able Expoſitors have thought that in this ſenſe it was, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> became guilty, and were blamed by the Lord himſelf, for taking the accurſed thing even that which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>Achan,</hi> Joſh. 7.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or a neglect of means to reform the provocations committed; and thus <hi>Ely</hi>'s
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:191877:34"/>neglect of a through reforming, and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the abominations of his Sons, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to wrath againſt him and his houſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>Many in <hi>New-England</hi> are guilty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking ſins by actual Commiſſion, and theſe kindle the fire, and are Fire brands in the hand of Gods wrath; and ſome by approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do blow up the fire, and are as the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows to make the fire of Gods wrath burn: and ſome by toleration, do in their practiſe ſay, Let the fire burn, will do nothing to quench it, and at laſt ſome come, who with their luke warmneſs, and cold practices, are but as a diſh of water dropping upon a great and vehement flame, but doth nothing effectually to extinguiſh the fire of wrath kindled and flaming by reaſon of provoking ſins, the Lord guid every one of us by his Spirit to conſider, and in a ſelf-examining manner to ſee and ſay, What have I done to provoke the Lord? <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.5, 6.</p>
                  <p>But as to fact, the provocations of <hi>New-England</hi> are proved by many witneſſes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The witneſs of the Miniſtry, eſpecially upon moſt ſolemn occaſions in the moſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick aſſembly, have as watchmen warned us of the Lords controverſie againſt <hi>New-England,</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:191877:35"/>and of the evil coming upon them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.7. and this warning was given not only ſince the Wars, but before that evil day come.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Witneſs that great Hand writing of our Rule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> publiſhed by their order in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of this Colony in a day of Faſting &amp; Prayer in that calamitous year, 1675. and many Writings and Orders ſince that, calling for a renewed Confeſſion of thoſe crying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations ſpecified in that Writing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in our former Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Witneſs the ſighing of thoſe whom the Lord hath marked in our <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> becauſe they do afflict and vex their righteous Souls for the provocations they ſee or hear of, <hi>Ezek</hi> 9.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Witneſs the ſelf condemnation, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Profeſſors have received within themſelves, and do frequently at this day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it one to another (ſaying) we and our poſterity are an undone people, if more be not done for Reformation, then yet is done, yea, who can ſay and prove it, that there hath been any conſiderable reformation wrought in any one matter of weight, after all that the Lord hath ſpoken and done againſt us:</p>
                  <p>But to conclude this Diſcourſe, let us ſtate one Queſtion more:</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:191877:35"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What are the Reaſons why the work of Reformation doth not proceed, but is hindred after theſe ſolemn Advertiſements by our godly Rulers, and after all the awful warnings from the Lords uplifted hand?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe ſome do not ſee what ought to be reformed, ſome who ſee, but have no heart to this work; ſome who have a heart, but little ſtrength; ſome who have ſtrength, but do not agree to carry on together every one his part, or they ſpend their labour upon a people who are under the power of Judicial impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some do not ſee what ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and thoſe are either.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Not convinced of a neceſſity of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but behave themſelves as thoſe did when Godly <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> zealous for Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſent forth his Edict by the hand of his Officers to command the People to return to the Lord, but ſome de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ided the Meſſengers, nevertheleſs ſome humbled themſelves, and the Lord gave them one heart to do according to the Commandment of the King and Princes reſpecting Reformation, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.10, 11, 12. the time haſteneth, when the bands of Mockers ſhall be made ſtrong, too ſtrong for them to break, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.22.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:191877:36"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Or theſe who do not ſee what ought to be reformed, do fix upon ſome leſſer matters of the Law, and ſpend the ſtrength of their zeal in reforming thoſe leſſer matters of the Law, but do ſuffer the more weighty matters of Judgement, Mercy and Faith to lye unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. and all theſe poor blinded Souls are ready to ſay as thoſe who were reproved for wearying the Lord, for robbing of God, and were commanded to return to the Lord, with a promiſe that the Lord would turn towards them; but they ſaid wherein have we wearied thee, or robbed thee? and wherein ſhall we return? <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.7, 8. theſe do not ſee what ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but theſe ſhall ſee whether they will or no, either to their Converſion or their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some who ſee a need of Reformation, but they have no heart to this work, and theſe are heartleſs either,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe the work of Reformation will reach the Idols of their hearts, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.3. and it may be ſaid of theſe as of them, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.10. are there not with you, even with you ſins againſt the Lord your God? and theſe not being willing to be cleanſed from the Idols of their own hearts, they are not hearty in the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:191877:36"/>uſe of the means of Reformation, but <hi>Rachel</hi>-like, they deviſe ſhameful excuſes to prevent the ſearch and diſcovery of their Idols, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.34, 35.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or they have no heart becauſe of the difficulties of the work of Reformation, as in <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s time, ſome were ſcared with affrighting apprehenſions of ſeeming impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities for them to carry on ſo great a work, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4.10. but what will theſe heartleſs Souls do? how can their heart endure? and hands be ſtrong in that day when the Lord ſhall pour out of his fury upon them? becauſe they had no heart to the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.14. and then muſt flee like a ſilly Dove without heart into the Net and Snare of Deſtruction, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.11, 12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Some who have a heart to the work of Reformation, but have little ſtrength, that is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Little outward ſtrength of Abilities, and opportunity; although (through the Grace of God) they have a ſufficiency of ſtrength to reform their own hearts and lives, and their own families; and though they have but little ſtrength, they have kept the Word of God, and not denied his Name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.8.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:191877:37"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Although theſe do lay to heart the ſins of the times, and their behaviour in Cloſet-Communion with God, and in their Families, and their converſe and converſation before all doth teſtifie for them, that they have a heart to Reformation, but they have not the power in their hands to do any conſiderable matter in the publick Reformation, and for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the abominations in the midſt of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> and theſe are the Lords marked ones, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4. ſealed Servants of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.3. and though they cannot deliver others, yet the Lord will deliver them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Some who have ſtrength, but do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to carry on together the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Its taken for granted of any who have but any common Notions of reforming work, that Reformation cannot confiſt in complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt others, and yet do the ſame our ſelves; <hi>Who art thou O Man who judgeſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and condemneſt thy ſelf, Rom.</hi> 2.1. nor in complaining againſt our ſelves, that we pine away in our ſins, and yet do not turn unto the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.10, 11. how can we then live? nor in publiſhing Laws, and profeſſed Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantings for Reformation, and yet after all theſe we go on in our Treſpaſſes, will not the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:191877:37"/>Lord be angry until he hath conſumed us <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But publick Reformation muſt be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on principally by thoſe who are in publick place; the Rulers of the Common-wealth holding and handling the Sword of Juſtice imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtially, and brightly, to the terror of evil doers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3. executing judgement in the Gates, and ſeeking truth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.1. And the Miniſters of the Lords Houſe managing the two edged Sword of the Spirit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. both in Doctrine and Diſcipline, making and keeping the difference clear between the clean and the unclean, the Holy and the Prophane <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.23. and then the People ready to ſtrengthen the hands of their Rulers, as he ſaid to <hi>Ezra, This matter belongs to you, ariſe and do it, and we are with you,</hi> Ezra 10.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But if every one do not practically a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to carry on according to their places and power, their part, the whole work of Reformation will be obſtructed in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or other.</p>
                  <p>If thoſe who are in chief place, and have the greateſt Power, ſhall leave the greateſt Burden of the work upon the ſhoulders of thoſe who are in inferiour places, and power, theſe will ſink under the burden or miſcarry in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:191877:38"/>the exerciſe of their power, and the work fall to the ground: but whatever the care and courage, faithfulneſs and zeal of chief Rulers may be, yet if Inferiour Officers be not Men of approved wiſdom and integrity, Laws will not be executed, and the Oathes of civil Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers will be violated; <hi>and becauſe of theſe Oathes the Land mourneth, Hoſ.</hi> 4.2, 3. for no publick Reformation can proceed.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Or whatever the care and pains may be of Reformers in faithfulneſs to God, and to his People, yet when they ſpend their Labour upon a People who are under the power of judicial impenitency:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Their labour will be in vain at preſent as to the work of Reformation; if that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had <hi>Moſes</hi> to be their Ruler, yet they will be ſtiff necked, and be corrupting themſelves, and one another, and be an unreformed and unreforming People, againſt whom the Lord had Sworn in his wrath they ſhould never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his reſt, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.30. And if <hi>Iſaiah</hi> were the Miniſter to a People under judicial impenitency, they may hear but ſhall not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, they may ſee but ſhall not perceive and not be converted, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And yet this is ſometimes the heavy work of Pious Rulers, thus to labour in the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:191877:38"/>fire, and ſpend themſelves, and be ſpent until at laſt the Bellows are burnt, and Lead con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and a melting in vain, the Wicked are not taken away; the Lord in juſt judgment hath ſaid, they ſhall be reprobate ſilver, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.29, 30. for after the moſt reforming means, they will not be reformed, but will treſpaſs more and more, and yet grow into a ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited and ſelf-juſtifying way: and the juſt and holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaying againſt theſe, <hi>he that is unjuſt, let him be unjuſt ſtill, and he that is filthy let him be filthy ſtill, and he that is righteous let him be righteous ſtill, and he that is holy let him be holy ſtill; and behold</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to give every man according as his work ſhall be,</hi> Rev. 22.11, 12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And yet the harder the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers is, and they found faithful in it, though labouring with a People under a judicial im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, and it is in vain as to that people: but yet their work proveth the more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, and they ſhall be the more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the eyes of the Lord, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.4, 5. 2 Cor. 12.15. and thoſe Rulers are in the way to ſee peace and truth in their dayes, as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah, Joſiah,</hi> and other godly Rulers had this favour graunted to them; although their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:191877:39"/>work was amongſt a People judicially decline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and running to ruine: yet ſeeing theſe Kings Ruled with God, and were fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thful to his Saints, the Lord gave them Peace and Truth in their dayes, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.19. and 22.20.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And although ſuch godly Rulers by their interceding with God, and faithful la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to reform a revolting people may preſerve them from ruine in their time; but yet if they be a people whoſe Rebellion and ſtiff neck is manifeſt while yet their godly Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.27. it is not all that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir Rulers can do will preſerve them at pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom many fearful Judgements; as thoſe which were inflicted upon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs, although <hi>Moſes</hi> was with them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.34, 38. and when the time is come that the Lord findeth none to make up the Hedge, and to ſtand up in the Gap before the Lord for the Land, <hi>then will the Lord pour out of his Indignation upon them, and conſume them with the fire of his wrath, and recompence their own way upon their heads,</hi> ſaith the Lord God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30, 31.</p>
                  <p>But O that we did hearken unto the Lord, that he might not give us up to our Hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Luſts, to walk in our own Counſels, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:191877:39"/>would ſoon ſubdue our Enemies, and turn his hand againſt our Adverſaries; but our time ſhould endure for ever, and he would feed us with the fineſt of the Wheat, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>But O that we did fear and flee theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual judgements more than any other judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for Jeſus hath ſaid, For judgement I am come into this world, that they which ſee not, might ſee, and they which ſee may be made blind: if ye were blind, ye ſhould have no ſin, but now ye ſay wee ſee, therfore your ſin remaineth, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9.39, 40.</p>
                  <p>And Oh that we could wreſtle and agonize by a ſpirit of prayer, that this Goſpel-vengeance may not be poured out upon our ſouls and the ſouls of our children! crying earneſtly to the Lord for his zeale, his ſtrength, the ſounding of his bowels. O Lord why haſt thou made us to err from thy wayes, and hardned our heart from thy fear; the people of thy holineſs have poſſeſſed it but a little while, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.15, 16, 17, 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="covenant">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191877:40"/>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:191877:40"/>
                  <head>THE COVENANT <hi>Which was Solemnly Renewed by the Church in</hi> Norwich <hi>in</hi> Connecticut Colony in New-England, <hi>March</hi> 22. 1675.</head>
                  <p>IN this Calamitous Year 1675, the Year of <hi>Jacobs</hi> trouble in the Wilderneſs, in which the Lord doth ſcourge <hi>New-England</hi> by the Outrage of the Heathen; a Year never to be forgotten.</p>
                  <p>And we who are in Church ſtate, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by our Pious Rulers, with other Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in this Colony, and in Conſeience of our duty moved to ſeek the Lord by Faſting and Prayer: and having conſidered the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars contained in the Writing ſent from our Rulers to the ſeveral Churches in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, and which we ought to keep in Record for ſucceeding Generations, in which they do advertiſe us of thoſe ſins, for which the fierce
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:191877:41"/>wrath of the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is poured o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t upon <hi>New-England;</hi> firſt by Blaſtings of the Fruits of the Earth, but in this year by cutting off the Lives of many by the Sword, and laying waſt ſome Plantations, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ruine to the whole.</p>
                  <p>Although to wonderment we have been hitherto preſerved in the midſt of the Heathen, yea, ſomewhat by means of ſome Heathen; but we feeling in this day of the Lords ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> as with a Candle, we cannot clear our ſelves (though through Grace) both we, and ours have been preſerved from thoſe many groſs acts of Prophaneneſs, and Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs, and ſuch like Scandals ſpecified in that Writing, and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire humbly to be thankful for ſome progreſs of Converting Work in ſome of the riſing Generation among us: But while we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold many unconverted Souls in this deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing year, and the ſame ſins working in us the cauſes of them, as in others; and a great degree of dangerous neglects of that which ought to be for the prevention of Apoſtaſie, and that the departings of the Glory of God from a People are by little and little, and not total at once: We do ſee cauſe to judge and caſt down our ſelves at the Footſtool of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:191877:41"/>Lord, being covered with ſhame. And ſeeing true Repentance doth not end only in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but is reſtleſs for Reformation, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Covenanting with our God is a means (through his Grace) in order to Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as we find in the tenth of <hi>Ezra,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Holy Scriptures and pious Examples: We do therefore this Day Solemnly Covenant to Endeavour uprightly by dependance upon the Grace of God in Chriſt Jeſus our only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That our Children ſhall be brought up in the Admonition of the Lord, as in our Families, ſo in publick; that all the Males who are eight or nine years of age, ſhall be preſented before the Lord in his Congregation every Lords Day to be Catechiſed, until they be about thirteen years in age.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That thoſe who are about thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years in age, both Males and Females, ſhall frequent the Meeting appointed in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate for their inſtruction, and to accuſtome them timely to the exerciſe of Church Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and theſe to continue belonging to this Meeting, ſo long as they abide under Family Government of Parents or others, or until they are come to the enjoyment of full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:191877:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly.</hi> That thoſe who are grown up, ſo as that they are in that reſpect, left to be at their own diſpoſe, ſhall be required to take hold of the Covenant of their Fathers hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth qualifications ſuitable to that ſolemn duty, or at leaſt that they hold forth a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encious endeavour in the uſe of means to prepare for the ſame; and if they be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent they ſhall be admoniſhed of their ſin; and if obſtinate, they ſhall be cut off from the Congregation of the Lord by that Dreadful Ordinance of Excommunication.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Whereas the indulgence of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in bearing with the evil Behaviours of their Children, their diſobedience, unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly geſtures, prodigality, and vain and unſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faſhions, or other things not becoming thoſe who are given to the Lord, is too mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and we are prone through fear or favour, or not obſervance to neglect admoniſhing ſuch, the Church doth appoint ſome Brethren to take notice of ſuch Children, and timely, meekly, wiſely, and faithfully to admoniſh them, and their Parents, as the matter ſhall require, and if private means doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, then to manage the complaint orderly in other ſteps.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Whereas the Sacrament of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:191877:42"/>Lords Supper, the Seal of Communion, ought o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en to be celebrated; for the prevention of neglect, we do determine (God granting opportunity) that we will be in the uſe of that Ordinance once in every ſix Weeks.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Whereas it is too often ſeen, that many through fear, or favour, or ſenſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability, do behave themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lves to their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as if they were not concerned in that g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt Duty of Admoniſhing their Brother for offenſive behaviours, unleſs it be in caſes wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rein they themſelves ſuffer wrong, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce love decayeth, and offences abound, and Chriſts Government, in works denied: We do ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mnly pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miſe, that we will in any w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rebuke, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuffer ſin to reſt upon our Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her, but deal faithfully according to Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Order.</p>
                  <p>And ſeeing we feel by woful Experience how pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne we are ſoon to forget the works of the Lord, and our own Vows; We do agree and determine, that this Writing or Contents of it, ſhall be once in every Year read in a Day of Faſting and Prayer before the Lord, and his Congregation; and ſhall leave it with our Children, that they do the ſame in their ſolemn dayes of mourning before the Lord, that they may never forget how their Fathers
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:191877:43"/>ready to periſh in a ſtrange Land, and with ſore grief and trembling of heart, and yet with hope in the tender mercy, and good will of him, who dwelt in the burning Buſh, did thus ſolemnly renew their Covenant with God: And that our Children after us, may not provoke the Lord and be caſt off as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Off-ſpring, but may tremble at the Commandment of God, and learn to place their hope in him, who although he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us a Cup of Aſtoniſhment to drink, yet will diſplay his Banner over them, who fear him.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191877:43"/>
                  <p>A BRIEF DISCOURSE Proving that the Firſt Day of the Week is the Chriſtian Sabbath; Wherein alſo the Objections of the <hi>Anti-Chriſtian Sabbatarians</hi> of late riſen up in <hi>Connecticut Colony</hi> are refuted.</p>
                  <p>By Mr. <hi>James Fitch</hi> Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Norwich</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Gal. 4.10, 11.</hi>
                     </bibl> Ye obſerve dayes, and moneths, and times, and years. I am afraid of you, leſt I have beſtowed upon you labour in vain.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Gal. 5.12,</hi>
                     </bibl> I would they were even cut off which trouble you.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Col. 2.16, 17.</hi>
                     </bibl> Let no man therefore judge you in meat, or in drink, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the New Moon, or of the Sabbath<hi>-dayes.</hi> Which are a ſhadow of things to come, but the body is of Chriſt.</q>
                  <p>Printed in the Year 1683.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:191877:44"/>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:191877:44"/>
                  <p>ARguments Grounded upon the Word of God, to prove that the Firſt Day of the Week is by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Appointment the Day ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Holy Worſhip, and ought to be kept Holy unto the Lord, according to the Rules of Sanctifying the Sabbath, and conſequently the Ceſſation of the ſeventh Day Sabbath in theſe Goſpel Dayes.</p>
                  <p>And then a Reply to <hi>John Rogers</hi> his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to ſome Queſtions ſent to him from the Honourable Governour of <hi>Connecticut;</hi> and likewiſe an Anſwer to <hi>John R.</hi> his ſeven Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions with which he concluded.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Arguments, the Queſtion is not now concerning the Name, whether to be called a Chriſtian Sabbath, which ſome take to be Analogically a reſemblance to the <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath;</hi> or whither to be called the Lords Day, which ſome have thought to be a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:191877:45"/>more Goſpel Name. But the Subject of our Diſcourſe at this time, is not concerning the Name but the thing, and far be it from me to imagine that I can add any thing to, or do ſo well as thoſe Worthies, Doctor <hi>Bound,</hi> Mr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shepard,</hi> and others have done in their Learned Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Diſcourſes upon this Subject, only I ſhall take ſome Arguments which to me ſeem moſt ſuitable to my preſent purpoſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt is from <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. in which the Apoſtle declared, <hi>that he was in the Spirit on the Lords Day:</hi> For the opening of which words to make way for the Argument we may Conſider:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> It was ſome particular Day in the week, which the Apoſtle calls the Lords Day: for his Scope is to notifie at what particular time he had the Viſions and Revelations of ſo great concernment to all the Churches in all Ages to the end of the World, and this he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Lords Day:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> Which was either ſome particular day, or ſome general name applicable to any day of divine Viſion, if ſo then the anſwer ſhould be the ſame with the Queſtion, and prove and make evident nothing, for the queſtion is what day he had theſe divine viſions
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:191877:45"/>and the Anſwer then ſhould be in the day of divine Viſions, far be it from us to think that the Apoſtle guided by the Spirit of God in every word he ſaid, could ſpeak ſuch nonſence: therefore it muſt be underſtood of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular day in the week.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It was ſome particular Day well known to the Churches of Chriſt to whom he wrote, by that name of the Lords Day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> For it was a Day well known to the Churches by the name of the Lords Day, or elſe unknown and obſcure, and would want an Expoſition; far be it likewiſe from us to think that the Apoſtle guided by the Spirit of God, and having undertaken to make known to the Churches in what particular Day he had thoſe Divine Revelations, ſhould put an obſcure and unknown name upon the Day by which the Churches could not know what he meant; therefore it is to be underſtood of a particular day well known to the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This particular Day ſo well known to the Churches by the name of the Lords Day, was a Day of divine Inſtitution a Holy Day:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> For it is called the Lords Day, either becauſe it was a day of divine Revelation, or a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:191877:46"/>Day by divine Inſtitution; but it was not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Lords Day, becauſe it was a day of divine Revelation, for as we heard before, this would be to ſpeak nonſenſe, and nothing to the Queſtion, therefore it was called the Lords Day, becauſe it was ſo by divine Inſtitution, and ſo a Holy Day.</p>
                  <p>Take one <hi>Argument</hi> more for the clearing of this, That which is honoured by the Holy Ghoſt in the Apoſtle, with the ſame honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and holy Title and Name as belongs to the Lords Supper, and other holy Inſtitutions is holy as theſe are.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> The reaſon is, for if the Holy Ghoſt ſhould honour this particular Day with as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred a Name of Honour, as Ordinances are, and yet not be a holy Day, it would be to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it above its due, and conſequently to degrade other divine Inſtitutions, but this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, but the day ſpoken of hath the ſame honourable title and name, as the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the Word of the Lord. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the particular Day well known to the Churches of Chriſt, called by the ſame honourable and holy Title or Name, as the Lords Supper is, and other holy Inſtitutions was the firſt day of the week.</p>
                  <p>And for the Proof of this, let us conſider
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:191877:46"/>Arguments of all ſorts, inartificial, and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial abundantly confirmed by the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, Light and Evidence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To begin with inartificial Arguments, <hi>viz.</hi> Teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of all the Churches in all ages, from the Apoſtles times, until you come nigh to our dayes; take Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s own words, <hi>It is unqueſtionable to any man verſed in antiquity, that all the Churches of Chriſt, Greek and Latin, Syrian, Ethiopick, Perſian, and Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ck called the firſt day of the week the Lords Day:</hi> and further he and other Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies have and do give the chalenge unto any one to cite out of approved Hiſtories, or from but one an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ent Writer, but one Church, or but one Chriſtian or but one Heretick, who did gainſay this but of late times. And what force there is in this Argument we may now weigh it; the Word of God ſaith, <hi>that the Teſtimony of two Men is true,</hi> John 8.17. this is granted of all who have but humanity, that it is legally true, and the contrary to this is legally falſe, and we may know what to judge of him that ſpeaks it: but the Teſtimony of all the Churches of Chriſt, from the Apoſtles time from age to age, may well have the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit which belongs to two men, and ſomewhat more, eſpecially if we conſider that it was not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:191877:47"/>poſſible all the Churches Eaſt and Weſt, thoſe who had no opportunity one with another, that theſe could convene or any wayes conſult to deceive their poor poſterity with a lie, by telling them that the firſt day of the week had the holy name of the Lords day, and was to be kept holy, when if it were falſe: but they all ſpake the ſame thing, becauſe they were guided according to truth, which came from the ſame ſpirit of truth, breathing in the Apoſtles, and guiding the Churches in the primitive time, to declare the ſame to their Children, and ſo to Childrens Children in all ages, according as it was ſaid in another caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.6, 7. and if <hi>de facto</hi> as they call it, concerning the fact, for that we now ſpeak of <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the firſt day of the week from the primitive time, was called the Lords day, if Hiſtories be of no uſe to inform us, or what they ſay ought not to be credited, although they generally ſpeak the ſame thing as to fact what was done, I know not of what uſe they be: but all the Books and Hiſtories of the Church of Chriſt concerning the time of the ten Perſecutions, and ever ſince, may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Flames as unworthy of credit: and let us never Write and Record any thing more for the benefit of Poſterity of this kind:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:191877:47"/>But I take it for granted that no ſober minded Chriſtian will agree to this whatever <hi>John Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> his judgement may be.</p>
                  <p>And if any do deſire to ſee more fully how it is proved that the firſt day of the week is the Lords day by the teſtimony of the antient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; let them read Mr. <hi>Samuel Cradock</hi>'s Book Entituled <hi>Knowledge and Practice,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Book, concerning the <hi>firſt Day of the week by Divine Appointment the Lords Day;</hi> in which Books may be ſeen the antient Writers cited in their ſeveral places and ages from the primitive time to the latter time, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting the firſt day of the week to be the Lords Day.</p>
                  <p>We have at preſent done with the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, as it reſpects Teſtimony.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But let us proceed to that kind of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which by the Learned is called Artificial, and argues from the Artifice, Frame and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing, and muſt neceſſarily be granted to be the ſtrongeſt way of Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> The Apoſtle calls the Day as it was by the Lord made, and as it is, or elſe he did miſcal it; the firſt part of this disjunct Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition muſt be granted, that the Apoſtle did call the Day as it is, as the Lord had made,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:191877:48"/>for none will dare to ſay that he miſcalled it, unleſs it be thoſe who have learned to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme. The Minor follows, that the firſt day of the Week was made by the Lord above any other day of the week to be the Lords Day in Goſpel times; and for the Proof of this let us now Conſider:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> this was the day in which our Lord roſe, <hi>John</hi> 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This was the day in which he appeared to the two Diſciples after his Reſurrection to teach them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This was the day in which he appeared to the Apoſtles, and gave them their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the Holy Ghoſt to enable them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.33, 36. <hi>John</hi> 20.19, 20, 21, 22.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And this was the day he choſe again to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, when <hi>Thomas</hi> was with them, <hi>John</hi> 20.26.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And this was the day promiſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of and ſulfilled as in the former par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  <p>It was the day promiſed in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.24. called the day the Lord hath made: ſpeaking by way of Promiſe and Prophecie of Chriſts Reſurrection Day, as it is expreſs in the words.</p>
                  <p>And that which ſome have mentioned in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.27. hath likewiſe its weight, that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:191877:48"/>the eighth day ſhall be the day wherein their Offering ſhall be accepted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> Take the Argument from hence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this was performed literally, or typically, if literally, then the eighth day which is our firſt day of the week, was Honoured and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified above the ſeventh day, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the Lords appointment: but thus it was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Goſpel times for that would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Numb.</hi> 28.9, 10. therefore, it is to be underſtood typically, <hi>viz.</hi> what day in Goſpel times the Worſhip of God, ſhall be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and that is the eight day which is our firſt day of the week.</p>
                  <p>And that day of his Reſurrection was the day of performing that great promiſe and prophecie, <hi>Thou art my Son, this day I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thee,</hi> for thus its expounded by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſte, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.33. God hath fulfilled the ſame to us, in that he hath raiſed up Jeſus again, as it is written in the ſecond <hi>Pſalm, Thou art my Son this day I have begotten thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For although Chriſt is the Son of God from everlaſting, yet this was the day in which he was declared to be the Son of God by Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. and the firſt day of the week was the very day for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.5. as <hi>Pareus</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:191877:49"/>doth more fully explain it.</p>
                  <p>And to conclude this, and though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect that thoſe who are under a penal blindneſs and deafneſs, will either give or take reaſon until the Lord ſhall give them an ear to hear, and an eye to ſee, and becauſe they ſay they ſee their ſin remaineth, <hi>John</hi> 9 41. Bot to help the mind and memory of thoſe who are ſenſible of their weakneſs, but are willing to hear and ſee: Let us gather up briefly that which hath been ſaid out of <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. as followeth;</p>
                  <p>The day called the <hi>Lords Day</hi> is ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular day well known to the Churches of Chriſt, otherwiſe it was in vain, and to no purpoſe for the Apoſtles to have ſpoken a word of the Day.</p>
                  <p>And this day called the Lords day was a Holy Day, otherwiſe it could not have the holy name proper unto holy things and holy time.</p>
                  <p>And that the day called the <hi>Lords Day</hi> is the firſt day of the week, this hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both by the Teſtimonies of all Churches in all ages, though cavelled againſt by ſome in late times, yet this their Teſtimony may well paſs for legal Teſtimony in any Court of Juſtice upon Earth, and they who oppoſe it
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:191877:49"/>muſt be legally condemned for Liars.</p>
                  <p>And more then all this it hath been infallably proved by the Word of God, and his Works, that the firſt day of the Week is the very day which the Lord by his Prophets foretold he would make to be the day in which above all other dayes we ſhould rejoyce, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118 24.</p>
                  <p>And with his Almighty hand he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it by the working of his mighty power which he wrought in Chriſt Jeſus when he raiſed him from the dead, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.20. And in this very day revealing himſelf to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as the exalted head of his Church and People. And in this very day Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Apoſtles, and breathing the Holy Ghoſt in the ſame day upon them, to impower and enable them in all things reſpecting their work as Apoſtles of Chriſt, and particularly by the Holy Ghoſt guiding the Apoſtles to ſettle the firſt day of the Week in all the Churches of Chriſt, as it is the Lords day and our Chriſtian Sabbath: but more of this in that which followeth.</p>
                  <p>And thus that which the Lord hath wrought according to his Word, may well paſs or divine Teſtimony in the Court of Conſecience, that the firſt day of the week is by Divine
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:191877:50"/>Inſtitution the Lords Day, and our Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
                  <p>And now let us proceed in the ſecond place to prove that the firſt day of the week, which the Lord hath made by his word and works to be the Lords Day and our Chriſtian Sabbath, was ſettled by the Apoſtles in all the Churches in the primitive time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> By their Doctrine, <hi>Secondly,</hi> By their Practice.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By their Doctrine, for for the clearing of this, let us conſider; <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.8.9.</p>
                  <p>Where the Apoſtle doth by his Doctrine inform us of a Reſt which remaineth to the People of God, and another day of Reſt; and to make way for the Argument, let us open that Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> he ſpeaks of a Sabbatiſm, ſo the Word in the Original is, a Reſt reſembled by the ſeventh day Reſt, ſpoken of in the third and fourth verſes, and by the Reſt in the Land of Canaan mentioned in the ſeventh and eighth verſes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This is another Reſt, and therefore ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day for this Reſt: thus in 8, <hi>&amp;</hi> 9 verſes, and I ſhall at preſent content my ſelf with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus</hi> his Expoſition until I meet with a better; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the Pſalms to which the Apoſtle
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:191877:50"/>had reſpect, did ſpeak of another Reſt, and a day of Reſt which is neither the ſeventh day Reſt, nor the Reſt in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but ſignified and exemplified by the one, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed out by the other and the Apoſtles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of this Doctrine may be expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ad sjunctive Syllogiſme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> Either it is of the firſt reſt of God in which he ceaſed from the Works of Creation or of that reſt in <hi>Canaan,</hi> or of ſome other reſt, and of another day of reſt, but not of the two former; and therefore the concluſion of the Apoſtle is in the 8th and 9th verſes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sabbath of reſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This reſt, and day of reſt ſpoken of by the Apoſtle remaineth, ſo it is expreſs in the words of the 9th verſe, which remaining pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, belongs to this reſt, intimating by this his Doctrine, that the other reſt, the ſeventh day reſt is removed, for the remaining ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the ſtability and permanency of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel reſt, and the day of that reſt, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of the thing ſhaken, that thoſe things which cannot be ſhaken may remain, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.27. The reſt on the ſeventh day, and that day of reſt was miſerably ſhaken by the ſin and fall of man, which brought the Curſe not only upon himſelf and his Poſterity, but upon
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:191877:51"/>the works of Creation; and therefore the Lord did not only threaten to deſtroy Man, but likewiſe to deſtroy the Beaſts, the Creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things, and the Fowls of the Air; for ſaith the Lord, it repenteth me that I have made them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.7.</p>
                  <p>Thus was the ſeventh dayes Sabbath which was a memorial of Gods reſting from, and complacency in his works of Creation, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Mans ſin, and Gods curſe upon the Creatures becauſe of Man, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment for the ſanctifying the ſeventh dayes Sabbath did remain as a hand-writing againſt ſinful and fallen Man, as other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Hand-writings did, until Chriſt comes and brings in better Ordinances, and a better day of reſt which remaineth as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle by his Doctrine inſtructeth us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Reſt and day of Reſt which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, is that into which Chriſt firſt entred, and at length did perfectly poſſeſs, and into which he leadeth his People, but Chriſt entred into his reſt the firſt day of the week, when he roſe from the dead, and at length he paſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the full poſſeſſion of the Manſions and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. and he that entred into his reſt ceaſed from his Works as God did from his, <hi>ver.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:191877:51"/>
                  <p n="5">5. The remaining of this day of Reſt is ſpoken of in the preſent tenſe; it is ſaid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there remaineth a Reſt, ſo that it is that which at preſent the people of God do poſſeſs although the perfection of it is reſerved for them when they ſhall come to the Manſions prepared by Chriſt for them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. the words being thus opened the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> That if the People of God have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day of Reſt which is not the ſeventh day reſt, but that which Chriſt doth lead them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by his own Example, and by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him who entred into his reſt in the firſt day of the week, then the firſt day of the week is the day of our Goſpel Reſt, and of our Chriſtian Sabbath, and conſequently a ceſſation of the ſeventh dayes Sabbath; but the proof of all theſe particulars we have in the former: and concerning Chriſts entring into his Reſt on the firſt day of the Week, I ſhall yet ſpeak more fully concerning that as I ſhall meet with it in ſome of the Objections of <hi>John Rogers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſecond place, to prove that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles by their Doctrine did ſettle the firſt day of the week to be our Chriſtian Sabbath, we may ſee in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.12.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:191877:52"/>
                  <p n="1">1. That which is there expreſt is by way of precept and injunction, for ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, he had given order concerning the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the Saints, and therefore not left it as a matter of indifferency or liberty, but whoſoever did neglect this, did tranſgreſs the Apoſtolical precept and order.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This order for the collection for the Saints was not only ſent to the Churches at <hi>Corinth,</hi> but to the Churches at <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſo that it was an order and injunction common to the Churches:</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The order did not only reſpect the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection it ſelf, but the time and day of it, that upon the firſt day of the week, let every one lay by him in ſtore, as God hath proſpered him: ſo it is expreſs in the 2<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> verſe, now the Argument follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> The firſt day of the week was either a common and indifferent day, or a holy day, the day of the Chriſtian Sabbath, but no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and indifferent day; for how could the Apoſtle by his injunction and order, make it neceſſary for the Churches to attend this work of mercy, collection for the Saints on the firſt day of the week, if it was but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon day, and thus eſteem one common day above another contrary to his Doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:191877:52"/>14.5. far be it from us to think that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle could ſo contradict his own Doctrine, but it was becauſe the firſt day of the week was made to be a holy day, and ſuch works of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are very ſuitable unto the day.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Arg.</hi> Or thus, the Apoſtle did order collection for the Saints to be on the firſt day of the week, either becauſe it was the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sabbath, or for ſome other reaſons, but I have ſo long waited to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r of ſome other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why the Apoſtle ſhould lay an injunction upon all Churches to have ſuch an honourable reſpect to this day, without any conſideration of it as the Lords Day and Chriſtian Sabbath, and all the Objectors and Cavillers againſt the firſt day of the week the Lords day, have not brought forth the leaſt appearance of any reaſon to the contrary, that I confeſs I begin to think, that the Opponents themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves, have received a Sentence of deſpair of giving any reaſon, only they have travelled and brought forth one poor Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that there is not a word ſpoken of a Sabbath here, and who ſaith there is? but the Argument is taken from the Apoſtles Order, and by Apoſtolical Order advanced the firſt day of the week above any other day, and that the reaſon of this is, either becauſe it is the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:191877:53"/>day of the Chriſtian Sabbath or for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon which never yet was brought to light, and therefore we conclude as in the former that the Apoſtle by his Doctrine did ſettle the firſt day of the week to be a holy day, a Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
                  <p>Now in the next place, concerning the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Apoſtles &amp; the practice of the Churches, of which much may be ſaid in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their attendance to holy Duties in the firſt day of the week, becauſe it was a day ſeparated for holy Worſhip, but at preſent we may conſider <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> it was a Church aſſembly there ſpoken of, for it is ſaid the Diſciples came together.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the end for the ſake of which they came together, it was for the ſake of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious duties, that they might partake of the Lords Supper called breaking of Bread in this place, as in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. and did not go alone without other Religious performances, <hi>viz.</hi> Prayer and hearing the Word Preached.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is ſpoken of as a cuſtom, and uſuall practice of the Diſciples, therefore it is ſaid on the firſt day of the week when the Diſciples came together. <hi>Paul</hi> having wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for and taking this opportunity to Preach to them, for he abode ſeven dayes among them, but this was the laſt day, his being
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:191877:53"/>ready to depart on the morrow, as is expreſt in the 7th verſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> Hence the Argument is, <hi>Paul</hi> and the <hi>Diſciples</hi> with him either kept the Seventh day Sabbath or the firſt day of the week a Chriſtian Sabbath, or elſe they kept no Sabbath at all, if they had kept the ſeventh day Sabbath, that was the day before this Firſt day of the Week, then they had a meeting after a Sabbath manner for Religious Duties, then the Evangeliſt would not have ſpoken of this Meeting on the Firſt day as the only Church Meeting of the ſeven dayes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles abode amongſt them; therefore it was the firſt day of the Week in which <hi>Paul</hi> and the <hi>Diſciples</hi> aſſembled, and kept as a Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
                  <p>Much more hath been ſaid by others, and I have ſomewhat more in readineſs to ſay if the occaſion calleth for it, and God giveth oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
                  <p>But at preſent having proved that the firſt day of the Week was by the Lord himſelf made by his Word and by his Works to be the Lords day, and our Goſpel and Chriſtian Sabbath, and his Apoſtles were guided by the Holy Ghoſt to ſettle it in the room and place of the ſeventh day, both by their Doctrine and by their Practice; we proceed to make
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:191877:54"/>Reply to <hi>John R.</hi> his Anſwers to the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And concerning his Preface to his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, I ſhall at preſent omit it until I come to his Concluſion and then conſider both his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face and Concluſion together, theſe and the Superſcription being to the ſame Purpoſe, and the ſame for ſubſtance.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. 1. The firſt Queſtion: <hi>Are not juſt and neceſſary Conſequences from Scripture to be taken for the mind of the Holy Ghoſt in Scripture, or elſe how ſhall we Anſwer the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts againſt the error of Tranſubſtantiation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John R.</hi> his Anſwer is,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ,</hi> If the Conſequence drawn from Scripture is agreeable to the Scripture and no wayes contrary to the Scripture, it muſt be granted truth, becauſe it ſpeaks what the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks. But as to the <hi>Papiſts John R.</hi> ſaith, they had no Scripture that ſaid a piece of Bread was the body of our Lord, or that our Lord was turned into a piece of Bread, or that Bread was turned into our Lord; for our Lord did not ſay to his Diſciples, <hi>Take eat this Bread is my Body,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did affirm, therefore they ſaid that which the Scripture did not ſay, ſo do you ſay that which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth not ſay, for you call the firſt day of the Week the Chriſtian Sabbath, but the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:191877:54"/>Scripture doth not; you call every firſt day of the Week the Lords Day, but the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth not ſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply</hi> The Reply to <hi>Iohn R.</hi> his Anſwer follows:</p>
                  <p>His Anſwer conſiſts of two parts,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> partly of a ſeeming Conceſſion granting that Conſequences drawn from Scripture and agreeable to Scripture are truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly</hi> he compareth us unto the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> for ſaying that which the Scripture doth not ſay, and the Argument he gives is, If we ſay the firſt day of the Week is the Lords day and the Scripture doth not ſay it, then we are like the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply is, that we have already proved that the Scripture ſaith, that the firſt day of the Week is the Lords day, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iohn R.</hi> doth falſely Reproach us, and I might ſay, that he that will hold to the letter of a Scripture, although contrary to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſcope of that and other Scriptures, is like the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their defence of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation from thoſe words, <hi>this is my Body:</hi> But <hi>Iohn R.</hi> doth hold to the letter of the fourth Command reſpecting the ſeventh dayes Sabbath, contrary to the command of Chriſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:191877:55"/>in the Goſpel and that which is moſt ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and proper ſcope of that command, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the former arguments, and more ſhall appeare in that which follows, therefore in this <hi>John R.</hi> is like the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. 2. <hi>Is not Reſt meerly due and proper to ſucceed Labour?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. John R.</hi> granteth that Reſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows Labour, and that God reſted on the ſeventh day after his ſix dayes work was ended.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 3. <hi>Was not Jeſus Chriſt as he was God equall with the Father, and as he was God Man was Lord of the Sabbath; he himſelf declareth in the fourth Command, and requireth Man to do the like by the Command?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. John R.</hi> his Anſwer is that Jeſus Chriſt as he was God was equal with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all things was created for him and by him, But <hi>John R.</hi> ſaith, the next part is an aſſertion, yet not a ſolid one in this caſe, for as Jeſus Chriſt was God he was commander of the Sabbath, yea the whole Law, but as he was Man, he was made of a Woman under the Law: And further <hi>Iohn R.</hi> ſaith, but if thou haſt reference to the Scripture, <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.28. which ſaith, <hi>Therefore is the Son of Man Lord of the Sabbath Day,</hi> he doth not ſay, God Man but the Son of Man.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:191877:55"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply to <hi>Iohn Rogers is,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> He grants that Chriſt as God, is the Commander and Lord of the Sabbath.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He denies him to be the Lord of the Sabbath, as he is God Man: to which the Reply is,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> By God-Man is meant, God and Man perſonally united, that is, the Son of God having aſſumed a humane nature into perſonal union with his Divine nature, is both God and Man; and if he be not Lord of the Sabbath as he is God and Man then he is not head over all things as he is God and Man, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.21.22. then not Mediator as God and Man, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. And the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he gives now follows:</p>
                  <p>For ſaith <hi>Iohn Rogers,</hi> as he was Man he was made of a Woman, and made under the Law, hence his Argument is, if Chriſt as a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n was made of a Woman under the Law, then as God-Man he is not Lord of the Sabbath. If this be good Divinity then let <hi>Iohn R.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſay, that becauſe he was Man, made under the Law, therefore as God Man he is not head of his Church and is not the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour, and as God Man he ſhall not return to be the Judge of the World; this is ſo far
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:191877:56"/>from being ſolid, that it is contrary to the frame of Goſpel Scriptures.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He argues from <hi>Mark</hi> 2.28. his Expoſitions are theſe, but if thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to that Scripture which ſaith, <hi>the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> he doth not ſay God Man but the Son of Man; whence his Argument is, if the Scripture ſaith that the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath. then <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> judgeth it is not a ſolid aſſertion to ſay Chriſt as God Man is Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> My Reply is, that if Chriſt the Son of Man be Lord of the Sabbath its either as he is the Son of God, or as the Son of Man, or as he is God and Man; not as the Son of God conſidered without being the Son of Man for the words are expreſs, <hi>that the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Not as the Son of Man, this <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> granteth to be too low, becauſe thus he was under the Law, and therefore it muſt be as he is God Man, that he was Lord of the Sabbath, and yet <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> ſaith this is not a ſolid aſſertion, but he hath given no ſolid Argument to the contrary, but that which fights againſt it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Only a Queſtion from hence he doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:191877:56"/>I find it to be ſo long winded, and yet ſo ſhort ſpirited as to any reaſon belonging to the Queſtion in hand, that I can hardly ſpare Pen, Ink and Paper to Tranſcribe it, but we muſt have it as it is:</p>
                  <p>Theſe are <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> his words; I ſhall propoſe a Queſtion in this matter, if in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it is ſaid, <hi>That the Man was not made for the Woman, but the Woman for the Man, and in Scripture the Man is called the Lord of the Woman, why then if the Sabbath was made for Man and not Man for the Sabbath, is not Man Lord even of the Sabbath day; for though a Man be Lord of his Wife, yet he ought not to put her away in reſpect of the Law of God that hath made thoſe two one, ſo likewiſe the Sabbath, though man be Lord of it, in reſpect it was made for him, and not him for it; yet by virtue of Gods command, ought not to prophane it: yet if in caſe it was ſo that Man muſt either omit the deed of mercy to Man, or prophane the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath by doing the deed of mercy to the Man, he ought to prophane the Sabbath and do the deed of mercy, in reſpect the Sabbath was made for Man and not Man for the Sabbath; for God hath preferred the Man above his Sabbath, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him for the Sabbath but the Sabbath for him; for in this reſpect God hath made him Lord even of the Sabbath day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:191877:57"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply to all this is, That all this is nothing to the Queſtion ſtated, and who knows not but God wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l have Mercy rather than Sacrifice whether on the Sabbath day or any other t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 4. <hi>Was not the work of Redemption as great, and Godlike as the work of Creation, and ſo worthy of Reſt and a memorial upon its finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. Iohn</hi> R. his Anſwer is, the work of Creation was the greateſt work that ever was, for it was the Creating of all things: and the work of Redemption the mercifulleſt work that ever was to Gods Elect, for by it they were redeemed: And foraſmuch as the God and Father of all things ought to be obeyed as that one Law giver, who created all things and commanded all, that the ſeventh day ſhould be kept holy in reſpect of Creation, ought to be obſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by reſting from Labour as he did, and that becauſe he comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed it: And foraſmuch as our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath redeemed Gods Elect by his body and blood, and appointed for a Memorial of the ſame Baptiſm and the Lords Supper to be obſerved by the Redeemed ones, he ought to be obeyed in the ſame, as God the Father in the other, ſo that both theſe works have ſome thing to keep
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:191877:57"/>them in memory by the appointment of the Workmen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply to <hi>John R.</hi> his Anſwer is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> He ſaith the work of Creation is the greateſt work, and his reaſon is becauſe God made all things: The Reply is,</p>
                  <p>That if the work of Creation be the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, then the work of Redemption is not ſo great as the work of Creation; but a work is greater or leſſer according to the greatneſs of wiſdom, power and goodneſs manifeſt in it, but the wiſdom of God ſhining in the work of Redemption, excels the wiſdom ſhining in the work of Creation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. wiſdom in a myſtery, and the power made manifeſt in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is greater than in Creation, called the exceeding greatneſs of his power towards them that do believe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19.</p>
                  <p>And for goodneſs to finners <hi>John R.</hi> cannot but confeſs it is the mercifulleſt work, and yet he denieth that a day ſhall be appointed for a memorial of this greateſt work; but as it is worthy of a Day, ſo the Lord hath appointed the firſt day of the week for that end, as hath been proved by the Scriptures abovemention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and therefore it is in vain for <hi>John R.</hi> to deny it.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 5. The fifth Queſtion is, <hi>Was not the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:191877:58"/>work finiſhed at the Reſurrection of Chriſt on the firſt day of the week, when he entred into his reſt as God did into his.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> John R. his Anſwer is, The price was paid as ſoon as the Sacrifice was offered, and the dead raiſed; but the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption as yet not perfected in us, for we are yet under the bondage of corruption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. but to ſay that Chriſt entred into his Reſt on the firſt day of the week I cannot, for he did aſſemble himſelf with his Diſciples af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Reſurrection, being ſeen of them forty dayes before he aſcended up into Heaven, and upon the day of his Reſurrection did eat with his Diſciples, and did travail with them, which was Labour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply is, that <hi>Iohn</hi> R. denieth that the work of Redemption was finiſhed, becauſe it is not finiſhed in us: Whence his Argument is,</p>
                  <p>That if Redemption be not perfected in Believers, then not finiſhed by Chriſt: but this is falſe reaſoning for want of diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between the work of Redemption and the work of Application: Chriſts work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption may be finiſhed although the work of the Holy Ghoſt as ſent from the Father and the Son to apply Redemption may not be
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:191877:58"/>finiſhed and is not in this life perfected to the Elect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> The ſecond Objection is, <hi>That Chriſt was not entred into reſt on the firſt day of the week, and his reaſon is, becauſe he aſſembled with his Diſciples, did eat and travail,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply.</hi> The Reply is, Either Chriſt was on the firſt day of the Week in a ſtate of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, or a ſtate of Exaltation: if in a ſtate of Humiliation, then his Reſurrection was no degree of his Exaltation, contrary to <hi>Rom</hi> 1.3, 4 <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.20, 21. if he were in a ſtate of Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then in a ſtate of bleſſed and glorious Reſt: And although there are divers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of his Exaltation, as his Reſurrection, Aſcention, Seſſion at the right hand of the Father, and his return at the laſt Day to be the Judge, but Reſurrection is one degree of his Exaltation and of his Reſt; and therefore he was entred into Reſt, although for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and confirmation of His Diſciples, he did ſhew himſelf, and by ſome ſenſible ſigns make it manifeſt that it was himſelf, that very humane nature which had ſuffered death, was raiſed, that he that deſcended was raiſed, and is the ſame alſo that aſcended into Heaven <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10.</p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:191877:59"/>
                  <p>Qu. 6. <hi>Did not Chriſt allow this to be called his Day, as the Sacrament is called his, or the Loras Supper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. Iohn</hi> R. his Anſwer is, I cannot ſay that ever the firſt day of the week was called the Lords Day, and therefore cannot ſay whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he allowed it or no, I know that the Cup which our Lord communicated to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they called it the Lords Cup, and the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at which they ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to communicate of the Bread and Wine, they called the Lords Table, and the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth that Day in which the Lord communicated to him thoſe Viſions in the Revelations the Lords Day, but what day of the Year, or of the Week, I cannot tell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply to this is, there hath been Arguments given of all forts to prove both from humane and divine Teſtimony, the word and works of the Lord, the Doctrine and Examples of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, that the firſt day of the Week was that very day called the Lords day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. and if <hi>John Rogers</hi> was asked who his Father was, he would be aſhamed to ſay he could not tell, and yet he cannot but know that as to humane Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt mony, there is more clear and infallible proof, that the firſt day of the week was called
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:191877:59"/>the Lords Day than he can have who his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was, this being the Teſtimony of all the Churches in all Ages, from the primitive time to this very day, until of late ſome few ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e riſen up and raiſed the Objection.</p>
                  <p>But beſides all theſe Arguments from the Scripture have been given to prove it; and if yet <hi>Iohn</hi> R. will ſay he cannot ſell, we muſt leave him to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnorance, and he ought not to be off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nded with us, and revile us, becauſe we do know.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 7. <hi>Did not Chriſt countenance and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Apoſtles in the practice and ſolemniza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that day in proper Sabbath Ordinances?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> His Anſwer is before, ſaying not that I know the Ordinance of the Sabbath is reſt to Man and Beaſt, for ſo God ordained in the fourth Command after the ſix dayes work to reſt.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 8, <hi>Are not Chriſt and his Apoſtles therein to be a pattern for Chriſtians to follow, and ſo vertually a divine Inſtitution?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. Iohn Rogers</hi> his Anſwer is, that the eighth Queſtion is anſwered by the Anſwer to the ſeventh, and the anſwer to the ſeventh was the ſame with the Anſwer to the ſixth, <hi>viz.</hi> that he could not tell, that he did not know, and thus he makes a quick diſpatch of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:191877:60"/>to the Governours Queſtions: But in this he is like thoſe who when the Queſtion was asked them concerning the Baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> whence was it, from Heaven or of Men? they reaſoned with themſelves ſaying, if we ſhall ſay from Heaven he will ſay unto us, why did you not then believe him? but if we ſhall ſay of Men, we fear the People, for all hold <hi>John</hi> as a Prophet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25, 26. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they concluded it was ſafeſt for them to ſay we cannot tell, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. Thus likewiſe if <hi>Iohn</hi> R. ſhould ſay, that the Patern and the Examples of the Apoſtles, reſpecting Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and particularly concerning the Sabbath, ought to be followed, then he knows it would be ſaid, why do you not follow them? and if he ſhould ſay, that their Example ought not to be followed by Chriſtians, this would be ſo un-Goſpel-like and un-Chriſtian like, and therefore <hi>Iohn</hi> R. concludes it is beſt for him to ſay he cannot tell.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 9. <hi>If the old Jewiſh Covenant be expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſundry Ordinances about time and place,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>altred, why not the time of the old Sabbath alterable by the Lord of the Sabbath upon a Goſpel account as a memorial of Redemption?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. Iohn R.</hi> his Anſwer is, I know not what thou doſt mean by old Jewiſh Covenant,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:191877:60"/>I know no Covenant in Scripture by that name, if thou doſt mean the Covenant which the two Tables of Stone, the Tables of the Covenant which did contain the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments which <hi>Iſrael</hi> did enter into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, by engaging to perform the ſame, which Covenant they brake, and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Wilderneſs for the ſame; God did ordain by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> Ceremonies as a figure of the Mediatorſhip of Jeſus Chriſt at this time at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> entred into the Covenant of works, to ſhew that there was mercy to be obtained by Jeſus Chriſt, though the firſt Covenant was broken by them; that is to ſay, upon Repentance and Faith. Now though the firſt Covenant which was dedicated with the blood of Bulls and Goats, and accompanied with many Rites and Ceremonies which were figures of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip of Jeſus Chriſt, which Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are done away, but none of them placed in the two Tables, for that Law is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and it is as eaſie by Gods Decree, for Heaven and Earth to paſs as for a tittle of it to fail: Now the other Law contained in the former Covenant, called the Hand-writing of Ordinances, which was nailed to the Croſs of Chriſt, which did contain meats and drinks,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:191877:61"/>New Moons and Sabbaths, which Sabbaths was beſides the Sabbaths of the Lord, but Gods ſeventh day-Sabbaths were commanded by the mouth of the Lord with an audible voice, written with the finger of God in Stone, death inflicted upon the breaker of it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply is this, <hi>John Rogers</hi> his Anſwer is full of confuſion, jombling the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works and the Covenant of Grace together.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Covenant of Works was made with <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Covenant of Grace may be conſidered either as Ceremonially and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally Adminiſtred, and this <hi>John</hi> R. calls the Covenant of Works, or as it is attended with Goſpel Adminiſtrations, and there the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ariſeth.</p>
                  <p>Whether another day might not be more ſuitable upon a Goſpel account than the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day Sabbath? and what reaſon doth <hi>Iohn</hi> R. give to the contrary? I confeſs I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to grow weary of forming his Arguments for him, becauſe I find it more difficult to find out his reaſon, and to form it for him than to anſwer it, and could even determine for the future, that if he cannot, or will not form his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:191877:61"/>Arguments himſelf, I ſhall leave them as I find them covered with darkneſs and void of form; but if there be any face of reaſon in this his Anſwer, at length it is, That the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day being commanded in the Decalogue is therefore unalterable: but we have proved that Chriſt hath altered it, and by the Holy Ghoſt guided his Apoſtles to ſettle the firſt Day of the Week the Lords Day and our Chriſtian Sabbath: and becauſe I ſhall meet with this Objection more fully in the next Anſwer, I proceed to that.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 10. <hi>Is there not room left in the Words of the fourth Command for the ſeventh Day to be altered, and our Lords day to be ſanctified by the Lord of the Sabbath?</hi> See the Preface of the Commannment. <hi>Remember the Sabbath to keep it holy,</hi> and the Concluſion only ſaith, <hi>the Lord bleſſed the Sabbath: and when the ſeventh day is named, it ſaith only is, and not ſhall be for ever ſo obſerved:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. John</hi> R. his Anſwer is No: there is no room, for the ſeventh day is the very day commanded, and Jeſus Chriſt hath left it upon Record, that it is eaſier for Heaven and Earth to paſs than one tittle of the Law to fail, and hath forbid his Diſciples for entertaining ſuch a thought in theſe words, ſaying, think not I
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:191877:62"/>am come for to deſtroy the Law; and again, ſaith he; <hi>For verily I ſay unto you, till Heaven and Earth paſs one jott or tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſs from the Law,</hi> who dare therefore at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſuch a thing againſt Gods Law, given in ſuch a terrible manner, being ſpoken by his own mouth, the Earth trembling at his Word, and ſo terrible was the ſight that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, I exceedingly fear and quake, and not only ſo, but the Son of God teſtifying that it ſhall abide as long as Heaven and Earth, as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpecified, threatning alſo any that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſuch a wicked act, ſaying, <hi>Whoſoever therefore breaks the leaſt of theſe Commandments and ſhall teach Men ſo,</hi> &amp;c. therefore who dare attempt ſuch a preſumptuous act againſt Gods Law, and Chriſts confirmation of the ſame Law, and what is that to purpoſe in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face and Concluſion, ſeeing the day command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is the ſeventh day and no other, ſo that Sabbath is proper only to the ſeventh day and no other: but as to the concluſion of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, ſome Tranſlate it, <hi>therefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeventh day and ballowed it,</hi> which is moſt agreeable, it being taken from Gods ſeventh day reſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.3. See <hi>Beza</hi>'s Tranſlation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.12. and death not inffli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon any ceremonial Law but Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:191877:62"/>but death upon the prophaning of the ſeventh day Sabbath: the Reply is.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply: Iohn</hi> R. in this Anſwer is fled to his ſeeming Fort, and he knows if he be driven out from this, that neither he nor any for the ſeventh dayes Sabbath, have any Caſtle nor Covering for their conceited confidence, but the ſcope of the Queſtion if rightly ſtated and plainly expreſſed is.</p>
                  <p>That a Sabbath as a Sabbath is firſt and laſt in the Precept, and ſhall not be changed, but the particular day is ſecondarily ſpecified, and is mutable as other poſitive Laws are, the Lord having reſerved a liberty to himſelf to change them according to his Royal pleaſure, and who ſhall ſay he hath done iniquity? And as for <hi>Iohn</hi> R. his Argument, ſo far as it hath any colour of reaſon in it, is. That ſeeing Chriſt came not to deſtroy the Law but to fulfil it, and that in every jot and tittle of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to change the ſeventh dayes Sabbath into the firſt day of the Week, and to this we ſhall poſitively and plainly Reply.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is that which may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an actual fulfilling in all and every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar point and duty required in the Decalogue, but Chriſt did never actually fulfil the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Duties of Parents to Children of a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:191877:63"/>to a Wiſe and many other particular points and duties contained in the Decalogue and yet his fulfilling all and every one of thoſe Duties which had any ſuitableneſs to his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and work, as he had opportunity in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God or Man, this is called a fulfilling of all righteouſneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is an actual fulfilling of the Law literally; and in this ſence the Prieſt in his Labour in Sabbath duties of his Office, might be ſaid to prophane the Sabbath, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.5.</p>
                  <p>And a fulfilling ſpiritually and finally accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true ſcope of the Law, and thus he was ſaid to be blameleſs, and ſo may we, if we keep that day holy which Chriſt hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as moſt ſuitable to Goſpel times and the moſt ſpiritual ſcope of the fourth Command, although we prophane the ſeventh day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To come nearer to the Text mentioned, Chriſt came not to make any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive change of the Law but to fulfil it; and therefore to make a perfecting or perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive change: And the Godly, Learned do note that the word to deſtroy the Law ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to diſſolve or pull it in pieces, Chriſt came not to diſſolve or pull the Law in pieces, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:191877:63"/>leave the wills of Men to a lawleſs liberty, but to bring in a ſtricter holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a more perfect Adminiſtration and edition of the Law, and this is expreſly his ſcope, and Chriſt himſelf expounds his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the following part of the Chapter, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. whilſt Chriſt gives a more ſpiritual expoſition than the corrupt <hi>Phariſees</hi> did, who did cleave to and pervert the Letter of the Law, as this <hi>Jewiſh Sabbatarian</hi> doth the letter of the fourth Command: but when Chriſt changeth the ſeventh day Sabbath to the firſt day of the week, that is the Sabbath from the ſeventh day of the week to the firſt day of the week, with reſpect to the commemoration, not only of the old Creation which is ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted unto corruption, but the new Creation the work of Redemption which ſhall remain: what deſtructive change is this of the Law in any one jott or tittle of it, and no more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for any to complain of a change then they had when Chriſt changed, and made water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wine; if <hi>John Rogers</hi> cannot chuſe but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth this Goſpel wine, yet let him not ſcorn and ſcoff at us, for our thankful receiving of it: And if <hi>Beza</hi> be in ſo good credit with <hi>J. R.</hi> as he ſeemeth to intimate, let him credit <hi>Beza</hi> in this matter alſo, who atteſteth that in
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:191877:64"/>an ancient Copy he had found it thus Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, That the Apoſtle had given order for the Collections in the firſt day of the week with this added the Lords Day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2.</p>
                  <p>But ſeeing this <hi>Judaizer</hi> and others of his perſwaſion have ſo wreſted this Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. we ſhall add one conſideration more for the clearing of the ſame, and our Argument is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> As Chriſt came to fulfil the Law, ſo likewiſe he came to fulfil the Prophets, ſo it is expreſſed in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. <hi>think not</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that I am come to deſtroy the Law or the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, I am not come to deſtroy but to fulfil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But Chriſt did fulfil the Prophets, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies by performing and anſwering the ſcope and end of the ſame, and by changing the Prophecies into performances: Oh moſt happy and glorious change, without which the Prophets their Prophecies could not have been fulfilled! this was far off from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive change of one jott or tittle of the Prophecies.</p>
                  <p>So likewiſe Chriſt did fulfil the Law, and particularly that Law the fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by performing and anſwering the ſcope and end of it, and by changing not the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath as a Sabbath, but by changing of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath from the ſeventh day to the firſt day of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:191877:64"/>the week, and this was no deſtructive change of one jott or tittle of the fourth Command, but a moſt happy and glorious change with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the glory of the Law-giver, and the good of his People, which bleſſed ends are more fully and perfectly attained by the change, than could poſſibly be by a ſeventh day Sabbath, as is more fully explicated in my Catechiſm; ſo that the fourth Command complains not, it is wronged not a jott, or tittle of it deſtroyed, no more than when veſſels of Braſs or Earthen Veſſels are turned into Gold and that which is leſs perfect is turned into that which is more perfect, for though the Law of God is ever perfect as to the time and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for whom it is fitted, and ſo as the ſeventh day Sabbath as it reſpected the time and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for whom it was fitted, but yet when the firſt day of the week is appointed by the Lord of the Sabbath as moſt ſuitable to Goſpel times, and the ſubjects of Goſpel Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; now that which was leſs perfect reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting this time and ſtate moſt give place to that which is more perfect, and in this the fourth Command is not deſtroyed but fulfilled, the Law being no Enemy to the Goſpel, but like <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> do kiſs one another upon the Mount of the Lord, and thus doth the fourth
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:191877:65"/>Command and our Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 11. <hi>Whether do you well, knowing theſe Arguments are pleaded and accordingly practiſed in all Chriſtian Churches and our Laws there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon founded, to diſturb our Peace, offend our Conſciences, oppoſe our Government, before you gave us conviction, either by writing or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when as you were left to enjoy your own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion in private?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which <hi>John R.</hi> his Anſwer is, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>I am willing to refer it to the Judgement of God whether I have done well or not well, who knows whether you have ſtood for his truth or I, but to ſay pleaded and practiſed in all Churches; I know it to be otherwiſe both by Books and Reaſonings, and as for the Laws reſpecting theſe things, I know no Authority you have to make ſuch Laws; for there is one Law-giver who is able to ſave or to deſtroy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the things as to matter of Worſhip: you ought to have been obedient to his Laws, and not to have adventured to make Laws for him, founding them upon notions, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come deſpiſers of his Laws, and perſecutors of thoſe which will worſhip God by his own Laws, and whatever you think of it, it is God oppoſeth you by us, wherein you act in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:191877:65"/>and not Govern according to his will and as for our not giving you conviction as you ſay you are ſo far from receiving conviction from our hands, that you would not give us liberty for to make our lawful defence, but uſe your unreaſonable power by preventing us of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful plea, and alſo we did write the firſt time we were brought before you, <hi>Iohn Allyn</hi> the Secretary being Judge, which was before you had any firſt-day Law, as ſince you have made, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not knowing then but that we ſhould have had liberty to have pleaded our innocency, but was forthwith took away by the Conſtable and not ſuffered to make our defence, being fined ten ſhillings a piece, and committed to the Priſon; and no Law of God or of this Colony produced to convict us by, which we look to be very unreaſonable: and then wrote we to the Court which was then ſitting but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained no anſwer; I have a Copy of it to this day with all our hands to it as we then ſent it, but being now in Priſon I cannot come at it, otherwiſe I might have ſent you a Copy of it at this time. And what I have met withal from ſome of the Miniſters reſpecting this matter, it will be too much for me to write now, to aſſert what oppoſition I have met with from their hands in not lending me an ear, I
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:191877:66"/>deny that we were left to enjoy our own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n private, foraſmuch as God hath hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them to us, He hath required us, that what he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h told us in darkneſs we ſhould ſpeak in light; what we hear in the Ear to preach upon the houſe tops.</p>
                  <p>The laſt thing in thy Paper is as followeth,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John,</hi> when you have anſwered theſe Queries in writing, then a Reply may be made by ſome ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hand, and publiſhed to the World, or you may ſend it whither you will, but further to gratifie Pride, conceit or your preſumption we ſee no need, nor to be for edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and to this added to the former, <hi>John Rogers</hi> ſaith, I having anſwered to thy Queries writing them at large, ſo as where my anſwers may be ſeen, they may be ſeen at large with thy reproachful Superſcription and falſe charge, with both the Superſcriptions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling Concluſion, I know not of one Word that is wanting that is in thy Paper, but is here exactly ſet down, and the Queſtion ſpake to.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>John Rogers</hi> further ſaith, I deſire now that theſe following things may be weighed and well conſidered; we have this many years ſuffered under the Government by Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Fines, and other Sufferings, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:191877:66"/>of Hereſie, and acting againſt Chriſt, and being Antichriſt, it muſt needs follow that if we are ſuch, it muſt needs be becauſe we hold ſuch things which are Erroneous, being corrupted; and if ſo, why do you not ſhew us wherein, and confute us by the Scripture? we are ready at any time to produce our Scripture proof for what we hold, for it doth indeed belong to us to prove what we hold by the Scripture, and alſo it belongeth to you to prove what you hold by the Scripture; for it is not our work to prove your Opinion, nor your work to prove ours, but the affirmative party is to produce the proof, now we are the ſuffering party, being judged by you as if we were Antichriſt, and called to an account by you: could we now have Juſtice at your hands, and you reaſonable Men, you would demand our proof out of Scripture and weigh the ſame meekly and uprightly: we call you not to an account about your Opinion, but you ours, therefore it is our Opinion that is in hand, and do you think it hath a good face on it, while you are afflicting us, and charging me to be Antichriſt, and acting againſt Chriſt, to put forth Queſtions to me about your own Opinion whenas I call you not to an account about it: but ſince thou haſt begun to queſtion
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:191877:67"/>about your own Opinion well may I.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reply,</hi> The Reply to <hi>John Rogers</hi> his long Anſwer, and to the eleventh Querie, I can find in this his Anſwer, neither Divinity nor Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, neither good Reaſon, nor good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but a throng of abſurdities and incivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: and as ſoon as they are brought near the Light their monſtrous deformities will be made manifeſt to any man who hath not a blaſt upon his reaſon.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Word of God ſaith, that we ought to follow peace with all Men, and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>John</hi> R. pretending holineſs proceedeth to diſturb the peace Eccleſiaſtick, and Civil, of Pious Rulers and Godly People, and appeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to God for a Judgement, like thoſe in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 48.3, 4. who ſaid <hi>they would truſt in God,</hi> but they were rebellious, and their Brow as Braſs and Neck as an iron Sinew.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He denies that all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt do keep the firſt day of the week, as it is the Lords Day, and aſſerteth the contrary: but if <hi>J. R.</hi> knows of any Church in antient times or of late times, it is pity he doth not help thoſe of his Perſwaſion who have been ſo often chalenged to mention one
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:191877:67"/>Church of Chriſt in former times, or one Writer, or one Chriſtian, or one Heretick, who did gainſay this until late times: But if <hi>J. R.</hi> hath found them out and yet they muſt not be known but lie in obſcurity, there we muſt leave him and his Churches at preſent.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God and his People hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen our Governour to be a Judge, but <hi>J. R.</hi> hath taken upon him to give him his charge, and both in his Preface and in his Concluſion, hath uſurped the power to judge, both our Governour and our Laws, contrary to <hi>James</hi> 4.11. and although the Word of God ſaith, <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but intreat him as a Father,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.1. and that we ſhould be ready to give a reaſon of our hope with meekneſs and reverence, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. But <hi>I. R.</hi> is bold to rebuke our Governour, Dictatour-like, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt appearance of meekneſs, but with a groſs appearance of irreverence, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wholly forgot what Titles of Honour <hi>Paul</hi> gave, not only to <hi>Agrippa</hi> the King, but likewiſe to <hi>Feſtus, Act.</hi> 26. civility may be in one where ſincere Converſion is not, and good Manners may be where ſaving Grace is not, but it is not a poſſible thing that ſincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and ſaving Grace can be in that Man in whom there is not Civility and good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:191877:68"/>And as for his aſperſing Complaints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Government, for proceeding againſt him, I have no call: nor is there any need for me to take the defence of our Rulers, they are well able to defend themſelves, and will in due time clear their exceeding lenity towards <hi>John Rogers</hi> and their legal proceedings, and wipe away all his reviling Aſperſions; and what hath been done by the Miniſters and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtians for the conviction of <hi>I. R.</hi> and his Company is well known to thoſe who are not meer ſtrangers: <hi>but reprove not a Scorner leſt he hate thee,</hi> Prov. 9 8. A Man that is an Heretick after the firſt and ſecond Admonition reject, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10.</p>
                  <p>So that means of Conviction are to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved with reſpect to the hope of good fruit but what the fruit hath been of the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of means upon <hi>Iohn R.</hi> is known to any who knows <hi>Iohn Rogers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whereas <hi>Iohn</hi> R. is called in that wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Priſoner of Antichriſt, and this and ſuch like expreſſions he calleth Revilings: I ſhall propound ſome conſiderations out of the Word of God to guid our Judgements.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> He that ſets himſelf in oppoſition to Chriſt in his Meſſengers, and in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Aſſembling of his Church, doth act
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:191877:68"/>the part of Antichriſt, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.18, 19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He that manageth his perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whatever it is againſt the Churches of Chriſt by an Antichriſtian ſpirit, is in this an Antichriſt, that is to ſay, not with that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Spirit as the Witneſſes of Chriſt are wont to do, by laying aſide the uſe of lawful liberty. As <hi>Paul</hi> in abſtaining from Meat rather than offend his Brother, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>By practiſing that which there is no Rule and Command for, unleſs it were at preſent for avoiding of offence, as <hi>Paul</hi>'s Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing <hi>Timothy,</hi> Act. 16.3. And obſerving o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ceremonial Rites for a time, although he was as clear in his Judgement in theſe things, and far more infallible than <hi>Iohn R.</hi> can be concerning his ſeventh day Sabbath.</p>
                  <p>And behaving themſelves before thoſe who are in place of Civil G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vernment, in giving a reaſon of their hope with meek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as in the forementioned place, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and ſuch like virtues have eminently ſhined in all ſufferers for Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But the contrary to theſe is an Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Spirit, when ſo far from avoiding offence, that there is a catching at an opportunity to lay a ſtumbling block in the way, not only of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:191877:69"/>the Prophane and the Heathen, and giving them an occaſion to Blaſpheme but to grieve thoſe whoſe godlineſs is manifeſt to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of all, this is practical Antichriſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm in a high degree.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He that preſently after his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Converſion, plungeth into the errors of Anabaptiſm, and moſt rigid Separatiſm and Enthuſiaſm more deep than ever they dip any in the water, and at length is left to fall from ſet and ſolemn ſeaſons of Prayer, and to deny the immortality of the Soul, at leaſt to dream that after its departure out of the body, it lies in a ſleep, and ſhall neither go to Heaven nor Hell, this is the Man who is proud, and hath dored upon his Queſtions until he knows nothing, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. This is the Man whoſe folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9</p>
                  <p>The Heathen Philoſophers, and the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral light of reaſon in theſe very Heathen, ſhall riſe up to condemn him. This is the Man whoſe deſtruction ſhall be ſwift, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1 And periſh in the gainſaying of <hi>Korah,</hi> Jud. 11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He that doth all the former under a pretence of Converſion work, having been notoriouſly ſcandalous in his life; and as ſoon as he pretends to be converted, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently leaps into Antichriſtian-practices and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:191877:69"/>runneth furiouſly on with an Antichriſtian Spirit, this is the Man whom the unclean Spirit finds to be empty, ſwept &amp; garniſhed, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns with 7 Devils worſe, &amp; the latter end of this Man ſhall be worſe than his beginning, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.44. And whilſt he acts in ſuch ſpiteful oppoſition againſt the Spirit of Chriſt in his Meſſengers and Communion of Saints, and in that Blaſpheming, Reviling or dirty manner with lies and ſlanders againſt the Rulers in the Colony and Church, if this man hath not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready committed the Sin unto Death, yet he is in the high way to that unpardonable Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, 27, 28.</p>
                  <p>But how far all theſe are applicable to <hi>I. R.</hi> I leave to his own Conſcience, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of others: I am only at preſent cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to declare the Rule out of the Word of God by which we ought to judge; and let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are eye-witneſſes, and ear-witneſſes of his practice give in their Teſtimony when they are called thereunto: But I conclude, that if the Spirit of Chriſt was not only in the Martyrs, the Witneſſes of Chriſt, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in our godly Predeceſſours, Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Davenport,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shepard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stone,</hi> and in many others in <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>New England:</hi> That Spirit that is contrary to the Spirit of Chriſt in thoſe Worthies is an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:191877:70"/>Spirit, and in whomſoever it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that Man is no follower of theſe godly Pred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſſors; and although we are an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and declining People <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>John Rogers,</hi> and thoſe who are of his fellowſhip do n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us in our declenſions, but in thoſe things in which we are followers of our godly P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors in thoſe very things they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Adverſaries againſt us in this day.</p>
                  <p>But now I ſhall haſten unto a Concluſion, <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> concludes his writing with ſeven Queſtions: The Preface to them is this; <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> ſaith, I deſire you ſince we are under Sufferings by you, that thou wouldeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and return me a direct Anſwer to my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Queſtions un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erwrit, without ſhifting or ſhunning the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iohn R.</hi> his firſt Queſtion is;</p>
                  <p>Qu. 1. <hi>Whether Sin is imputed where no Law is?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> That ſeeing the Law, whither Moral or Goſpel, contains a Platform of well-doing, the contrary to this is Sin, and if no Law then no tranſgreſſion; but Chriſt is our Judge, our Law-giver, and our King, and he will ſave us, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.22. and he hath given us his command to keep the firſt day of the week holy as the Lords day: And the <hi>Moſaical
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:191877:70"/>Law</hi> reſpecting the ſeventh day Sabbath, in which <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Rogers</hi> truſteth, ſhall condemn him for his diſobedience againſt the Law of Chriſt, which is Lord of the Sabbath, as we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved already; and thus he hath an Anſwer to his firſt Queſtion, and likewiſe to his ſecond Queſtion, <hi>Whether there can be Tranſgreſſion where no Law is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> his third Queſtion followeth;</p>
                  <p>Qu. 3. <hi>Whither or no God hath given Laws ſufficiently to reprove ſuch as are Tranſgreſſors, or is ſhort in his Laws and ſo need many Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Gods Laws are perfectly ſufficient, and they need no Aſſiſtants, but we need Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to look to the Application and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them againſt Malefactors, and to be a terror to evil Doers; and beſides many other Reaſons to prove this, the experience of <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> his behaviour may be ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us that the government have need of Aſſiſtants, although the Law it ſelf needs none.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 4. <hi>Hath God any Law to forbid work on the firſt day of the week, and that gives liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to work on the ſeventh?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take likewiſe his fifth Queſtion almoſt the ſame with the fourth, and then we ſhall anſwer them together.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:191877:71"/>
                  <p>Qu. 5: <hi>Hath God by any of his Meſſengers or otherwiſe in Scripture called the firſt day of the week the Chriſtian Sabbath, or is it a humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, if not humane, quote the place in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, for a thing is known by the name of it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> I Anſwer both to the fourth and fifth Queſtion, I have proved it already by many Arguments from aforementioned Scriptures, that the firſt day of the week is by Chriſts Commandment the day appointed to be the Lords day, and our Chriſtian Sabbath, and therefore I refer him for an Anſwer to that which hath been already ſaid.</p>
                  <p>Qu. 6. <hi>If any Sect produce Conſequence from Scripture, as the Judge to uphold their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and it appear to be altogether contrary to the plain Word of God in the Scripture, whither or no I ſhould look at it to be conſequence or blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Sect?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Conſequence from Scripture is either a neceſſary Conſequence, and being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture, is of as full force as any plain Scripture, as <hi>John Rogers</hi> granted in his Anſwer to the firſt Queſtion, or elſe it is a Conſequence ſeemingly deduced from Scripture, but is really a perverting of, and contrary to the Scripture, as ſome unlearned and unſtable, who wreſt the Scriptures to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:191877:71"/>their own deſtruction, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. and then it is far off from being of the ſame force with the Scripture: But we have given <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> neceſſary deductions from plain Scriptures in the Old and New Teſtament, to prove that the firſt day of the week is the Lords day, and our Chriſtian Sabbath; and it is in vain for <hi>Iohn R.</hi> to deny this until the Arguments be confuted.</p>
                  <p>Qu 7. <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> his ſeventh Queſtion, <hi>Whether or no there be a poſſibility to take out the day commanded out of the fourth Commandment, and put in one of the ſix working dayes, in the room thereof, and not alter one jott or one tittle of the former Law, if there be a poſſibility of ſuch a thing, or ever ſuch a thing was?</hi> I deſire a Copy of it may be ſent me to the Priſon as ſoon as may be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> My Anſwer to this ſeventh Queſtion is, that I have already proved in my Reply to his Anſwer to the tenth Queſtion, that this change of the Sabbath from the ſeventh day to the firſt day of the week is no deſtructive but a perfecting change, and ſo far from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the Law in a jott or tittle of it, that it is a fulfilling of the Law as really and fully as the performances of Prophecies are the fulfilling of Prophecies, and it is too late for
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:191877:72"/>
                     <hi>John Rogers</hi> now to queſtion, whither that be poſſible to be done which is already certainly performed and done as we have proved al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; and as for ſome fragments of Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Cavils which <hi>I. R.</hi> hath gathered out of ſome late Authors, and yet if all theſe be put together he is unable to defend his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day Sabbath.</p>
                  <p>And it is as poſſible for <hi>I. R.</hi> to hinder the charge of the Moon as he can hinder the change of the ſeventh day Sabbath, ſeeing it is founded upon the works of Creation which is given to change: but who can hinder the ſtability &amp; immutability of the firſt day of the Week, the Lords day; which is grounded upon the unchangeable work of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, according to an immutable and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant: And if it be not poſſible for <hi>I. R.</hi> yet to ſee the reaſon of this but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire at his legal light, and deſpiſe Goſpel vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: <hi>Behold ye deſpiſers wonder and periſh, for I work a work in your dayes, a work which you ſhall in no wiſe believe, though a man declare it unto you,</hi> Act. 13.41. and yet thoſe who have the Revelations of the Spirit of Wiſdom in the Goſpel, ſhall ſay, this is the Lords doings, it is marvellous in our eyes, this is the day which the Lord hath made; <hi>Save now I beſeech
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:191877:72"/>thee O Lord, bleſſed is he that cometh in the Name of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 118.23, 24, 25, 26.</p>
                  <p>And if he that deſpiſed the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and particularly did prophane the ſeventh day Sabbath was ſo ſeverely puniſhed, as <hi>Iohn</hi> R. did note, of how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath deſpiſed the Goſpel Commandment, and particularly the Lords day the Chriſtian Sabbath, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Inſtitution of Chriſt which he hath by his Blood purchaſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29.</p>
                  <p>And thus I have done likewiſe with <hi>Iohn R.</hi> his Queſtions at preſent; and if <hi>I. R.</hi> or any for him ſhall undertake to make a Reply to that which hath been ſaid, I expect they ſhould anſwer my Arguments <hi>interminis,</hi> according as they are in the frame and method of them: I do not intend for the future to trouble my ſelf with an Anſwer to ſuch Lax Diſcourſes as have nothing of the frame of an Argument with them.</p>
                  <p>And thus at preſent I have done ſpeaking to Man, but this I may ſay, <hi>Oh Lord, I have not deſired the woful day, that which came out of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ips was right before thee, be not thou a terror to me, thou art my hope in the day of evil,</hi> Jerem. 17.16, 17.</p>
                  <p>And if in any thing I have ſaid for matter or
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:191877:73"/>manner, or in any reſpect whatſoever I have erred, let it not be confirmed but confuted, and let me be convinced: but if that which hath been ſaid be according to thy Holy Word revealed by the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es of the Lord Jeſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let thoſe who do, or ſhall oppoſe, be converted, and repent of this their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of their heart may be forgiven them, or elſe let them be confounded and cut off. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.22 <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the Plague is come into a neighbouring Plantation, and ſome Families already ſhut up, the Lord have mercy upon them, and humble us deeply for our great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulneſs and eſpecially for our prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y: what is the cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of this ſo fierce wrath to let looſe a Spirit of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Deluſion thus to rage, that thoſe who received not the love of the truth may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up to believe a lye, and damned that have pleaſure in unrighteouſneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, (2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 10.11, 12) And whilſt ſome riſe up that they might caſt down the Chriſtian Sabbath, under a pretence of advancing the ſeventh day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; <hi>Oh Lord, let not the evil one prevail with the prophaneneſs of others to cauſe them to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect holy time and holy things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:191877:73"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Do good O Lord to thoſe that are good, and to them that are upright in their hearts: As for ſuch as turn aſide to their crooked wayes, the Lord ſhall lead them forth with the workers of iniquity, but peace ſhall be upon Iſrael,</hi> Pſal. 125.4, 5.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Decemb. 12. 1682.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>JAMES FITCH, <hi>Senior.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
